for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
angels, demons and saints in our time
Many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism to see and to know
reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live college show, focused on enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and unseen
as made by God and ex-
experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, good evening, giant killers,
dragon slayers and hammers of hydrants.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast
and it is episode 119.
My co-host, Father Stephen D. Young,
the half-oracomunculus horker,
is with me straight from the swamp.
And Lafayette Louisiana,
and Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Emmaus, Pennsylvania,
perched precariously top,
the arcane tower of podcasting,
hovering dozens of stories,
but it disused...
gateway to the underworld. And we know I like the voice of Steve, but one of these
anniversary episodes. Yeah, I think I think just for one episode we need to do
the opening with AI Morgan Freeman. I'm throwing that out there. I will see
what I can do. I will see what I can do. I can just do my best Morgan Freeman
impression. No, that would probably not be good. Or if you want to even deeper
cut we could do
like AI Harrison Ford and have it be like the theatrical cut of Blade Runner.
Just make the show worse.
Nice. Wow.
So if y'all are listening to us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346.
And you can talk to us and we'll get your calls beginning in the second half of the show.
And Mike Marsapan again will be taking your calls.
Last time.
the Lord of Spirit's podcast. We talked about the authority of Moses as it was passed on in
succession from him to Joshua and then to the Sanhedrin, the elders of Israel. And this time,
so this is a two-parter, we're turning to the authority of the apostles and their successors.
So are they, I mean, are they connected in some way is the authority that apostles from Moses?
Chad.
Kinda.
So, yeah, this is...
the second part of a two-parter. Yes, that's right. This episode is not itself a two-parter.
Like we're not going. That's correct. We're not going full Thomas Aquinas and like.
You know, part one, part one of part two, part two of part two, right? We're not doing that with
you. Right? Where this is just two of two.
And now I need a Chuck Willary drop in. Oh man. Is he still alive? He is. He's become a
Okay.
right wing pundit. How about that? I mean, like D tier right wing pundit. Like nice. Wow.
Who could have predicted that? Yeah. I guess see it. All those bad dates go down. I mean, you could
have just become a, I don't know how you classify Pat Sage act these days, but he's sort of a culture
critic, but a friendly culture critic. Yeah. And I think Chuck Willary saw all these just horrible
relationships and modern
dating and said we need to get back to some traditional values.
When full trad rules. Yeah. I think that's what happened.
Or he was broken, Bill Riley offered him some money. I don't know. Something like that.
I think this might be our first Chuck Woolery reference in the whole show.
It is possible. Yeah. I don't know. Super fans. Let us know.
Have we mentioned Chuck Woolery before?
I'd be surprised if I haven't made some kind of two and two reference at some point.
But yeah, Chuck Woolery was like the upscale new generation dating game.
No he actually, he is dead as of November.
Oh, he just died recently.
Yeah, he was 83.
There we go.
Yeah.
end of his life he had a brief resurgence as a.
Yeah, man, here right wing radio personality and he apparently also worked as a wine consultant for while in Columbus, Ohio
Huh and and since I'm looking at his Wikipedia entry as one does he served aboard the USS Enterprise the aircraft carrier
How about that?
Maybe this is what people tune in for they're not not really interested in theology. They want to hear father Andrew googling
the
the late eighties. I love connection. He was we look, he did we look
fortunate to like Pat say Jack for a while in the late seventies. Yeah,
no, he was like, so yeah, so people forget that like the dating
game, it was actually kind of a game show. Oh, yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
And love connection like what likewise, they followed the game show
model. Yeah. But love connection as far as I know,
the
unlike the reality show cheaters, no one was ever killed.
Well, that's yeah.
Wow.
And apparently see this is something I also didn't know.
He had a musical career in psychedelic pop and in country.
I'm doing all kinds of fun things today.
Yeah.
So I'm just going to go ahead and get us back to talking about the authority of Moses.
If I
for you to come up with a segue from Chuck Woolery to that. Like we know that's not going
to happen anytime soon. So did Chuck Woolery lay hands on Pat Sage Jack? Call in, let us
know. That could be interpreted a lot of ways too. Like that could be a who would win
in a fight kind of thing. Yeah. I suppose now Sage Jack, because he's alive. But yes, and
you know, in a previous era. But anyway, so yeah, last time we were talking about Moses
You
and sort of the nature and structures of the authority that Moses had, which is not necessarily
the way a lot of people think about it. Like, yeah, Moses is a prophet and Moses was the
leader of Israel. But the particular emphasis that Mosaic had this unique authority to make
rulings, right, to take wood.
God had revealed and said to him and then apply it authoritatively in the life of the people of Israel.
Both in response to questions resolving disputes and generally laying out the path in different circumstances,
like we pointed to the way Passover was celebrated when they were celebrating it in a camp in the wilderness versus how it was celebrated by Moses instructions.
once they were in...
the land and settled, when those new practical realities took hold, he reapplied the same
commandments from God to that new situation, and in both cases it was equally authoritative.
We talked about how that authority didn't end with Moses, then it wasn't just Moses
made all these rulings, and we recorded them in the Torah.
It's a now we're good.
All questions answered.
I answered all disputes resolved. Everything is totally clear.
Yeah, nothing will ever have to be applied because society will never change in any fundamental way
and
so there is
Is God promised a succession of
of prophets
after him
We talked about their qualifications. We also talked about how they had that same authority to take into apply and in fact that
What you have sort of codified in the rest of the Old Testament in different ways
you know, whether we're talking about Psalms or probs.
or the prophets, proper or what are sometimes called the historical books or the former prophets.
Those are all in various ways taking the revelation of God in the Torah, the revelation of God
to Moses that was shared by his successors and applying it to the history of Israel,
to everyday situations in the life of Israel, sort of in different ways in different contexts.
and
We talked about how there was a sort of physical manifestation of this authority being handed
out from Moses.
This was not just a purely like, oh, hey, look, this guy has shown up and he seems kind
of like Moses.
He has sort of charismatic authority, right?
that there was an actual laying on of hands that we see begin.
with Moses laying his hands on Joshua
and passing that authority to him.
In a very literal way.
So there was both a,
what we might compare to a soul
of the succession from Moses,
which is the succeeding prophets
sharing the experience of God
that Moses had
in different ways into different extents.
And then the sort of body, the physical or material element of that would be the laying out of hands.
Right.
And so toward the end we talked about the fact that you could have a false prophet, a prophet who had the physical part, who had the laying out of hands,
but did not share the experience.
Right, you could have faithless prophets, right, just like in the same way that there were Israelites who were circumc-
sized on the eighth day, but went on to become wicked people, right? And not sort of fulfill
the calling that had been placed upon them. And that this means was given in Deuteronomy
for determining sort of, how do I know that this is the guy who's making the authoritative rulings,
as opposed to the other
other category, the false prophet. And we talked about how that was typically done through
signs, right? God gave signs through the prophets, right? And when those signs were demonstrated
to be true, then that was a way of God revealing who the prophet who had that authority was
at any given point in time.
Uh...
to the people of that region.
And we talked about how we start out with just Moses
when they're a camp of the wilderness,
but then once they get settled in the land
and they are spread out,
we see that there are a bunch of prophets in any given time
who are all utilizing this same kind of authority
in their respective communities, right?
You've got the Northern Kingdom of Israel,
the Southern Kingdom of Judah.
You have different prophets active,
sometimes at the same time in those two places
and even within Israel or within Judah.
So, as we get to the New Testament, people begin to perceive as Jesus of Nazareth comes
out and is publicly preaching and teaching.
He is speaking as one who has authority.
He is speaking as someone who is making these kind of authoritative pronouncements and
and Rolex.
Yeah.
And at the same time, there are certain parties within Galilee and
and Judy in life who don't always like what he's saying and doing.
Or have some disagreement.
And so we get sort of repeated instances of people asking him questions like,
what authority do you do these things?
Who gave you this authority?
We talked about some of these last time, right?
Um.
sort of asking for his bonafide, who laid hands on you, right? Who made you the right?
And of course they haven't keyed it on Jesus being the Messiah or the logos incarnate, obviously,
right? But so they're asking these questions and sort of the culmination of that
comes as described in St. Matthew's Gospel, when the religious authorities come to him and demand a
the sign.
They say, okay, well, we'll find out for sure whether you're the real deal or not, right?
Give us a sign so we can test this thing.
Yeah.
Yeah, so this is in Matthew chapter 16, starting with verse 1.
And the Pharisees and Sadducees came and to test him, they asked him to show them a sign from heaven.
He answered them, when it is evening you say it will be fair weather for the sky is red.
red and in the morning it will be stormy today
for the sky is red and threatening. You know how to interpret the appearance of the sky,
but you cannot interpret the signs of the times, and even an adulterous generation seeks for a sign.
But no sign will be given to it except the sign of Jonah. So he left them and departed.
Right, so they didn't see the sign or would have opened up their eyes.
You know when I was a
an undergraduate decades ago now. I took a philosophy 101 class, and I recall the professor,
he was teaching the platonic concept of the forms, and the example that he gave was the form
of the Scandinavian pop band. And so then he mentioned several instances of this, you know,
you know, ABBA Ace of Base.
And to this day, now whenever I hear any reference to them, I immediately think about
Platonism. It's weird. When you said form, I thought you were going for form of water, shape of a
wilderness. Nice. Yeah. Deep cut there. That is. I mean, that's from the right. So what's going on
here? One might ask, well, wait, I thought they were supposed, I thought signs were how they were
They were supposed to check out telephulse profit for real profit.
Right. But note here, and I could have talked about this last time,
frankly, from Isaiah chapter seven, but we've gone over that a lot.
Could have beat it to death. But first of all,
Christ has been doing a lot of signs.
There's a bunch up to this point. So there's a whole bunch of things
that these Pharisees understood perfectly well. We're signs that the Messiah
headcut.
We're signs of the messianic age, right? Like blind people seeing lame people walking, right, etc. etc.
Um, which is happening, right? When Matt, by the time we get to Matthew 60, like,
Price has healed a lot of people. He's cast out demons. He's been teaching publicly, right?
They have, they have all the signs they need.
but they've you know as anyone can right with any
argument or any proof, right? If you really don't want to believe it, you will find a way to discount it and they have, right?
And so they're demanding this sort of further sign. They're doing it to test him, right?
So the idea is signs are given by God, right? And a human who is pious, a human who is seeking God,
a human who is seeking God's authority, right, will recognize them. That's why Christ gives these examples of,
you know, hey, you see these signs in nature and you recognize what that means, right? But you see all this stuff I'm doing and you're like,
like boom, right? Meaning they're motivated to not believe. Right? And what that really
reveals the fact that they are motivated to...
to not believe reveals the kind of wicked generation it is that he's speaking to.
Meaning that there's nothing he could do at that moment, right? There was no
miracle, there was no wonder, there was no sign he could do in front of them that
they wouldn't have found some way to dismiss. And we know this from the rest of
the text of Matthew, right? He casts out a demon and they're like, oh he cast out
demons by the Prince of demons. Like, right? Well, I mean,
Right? And so,
Christ doesn't bother doing,
doing anymore, right?
Other than making this reference to the sign of Jonah,
which has something to do with the resurrection, but you can go and see past episodes about that.
But so these signs are sent by God.
They're not things that humans demand.
Right. And the reference I made to Isaiah 7,
and if you go back there without getting into that hole.
thing all over again. Isaiah comes to the king and says, ask God for a sign. He says, Oh,
no, I couldn't. Right. He's sort of very pious. Isaiah says, Okay, well, God's going to
give you what anyway here it is. Yeah. It's not proof that that should be demanded. It's
a gift. Right. Right. So we begin with that clarification. Right. Surrounding, surrounding
videos but
There are some folks who stand in this line from Moses at the time that Jesus is traveling
and preaching in Galilee and Judea and doing these miracles.
And those people are the Pharisees, the Sanhedrin in particular who are Pharisees.
They made sure to keep the Sadducees out at this point in history.
and uh...
And then the scribes who we sometimes see, or in one translation that we're going to read
later tonight, I think the lawyers.
What do you lawyers, the experts in the law?
But that's the Torah, right?
These are scribes who are sort of in training to for the laying out of hands for sort of
of ordination, right?
These are the folks.
Right.
And based on sort of the Sunday school version of the gospels we get, some folks may
be thinking, oh, well as soon as Christ shows up on the scene, those guys are done.
Yeah, they have no authority.
Right.
Any authority they might have had is gone.
Yeah.
That's that what Jesus says, like it all.
And not only is it not what Jesus says, you could go to pretty
which the harshest passage, right, where Christ is just railing against the Pharisees, right,
for all the things wrong with the Pharisees. And he doesn't deny the authority they've
received from handed down from Moses while he's excoriating them.
But I thought Jesus was offering a relationship not religion.
I know, well you have to understand.
being really unChrist-like in this path. Very mean. Very mean. Very judgey.
So, but we're talking about Matthew 23, and this is where Christ pronounces
woes upon the Pharisee, and woe to you just doesn't have a ring
like to us, it just sounds antiquated, right? But uh...
Like for example, the scholars version back in the 90s, they translated it as damn you.
The same woe to you is sort of what is basically saying you're going to hell.
You're on the road to hell right now.
Now keep in mind, as Christ says that to the Pharisees, he is saying that to the Pharisees,
meaning he's trying to get them to get off that road.
Yeah, if he just wanted them to go then he wouldn't bother to say it.
He would ignore-
them. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So Matthew chapter 23, which we're going to read the whole thing.
But I will stop it. I will jump in. Then Jesus said to the crowds and to his disciples,
the scribes and the Pharisees sit on Moses' seat. So do and observe whatever they tell you,
but not the works they do for they preach. So they do not practice. Right there. Right. They sit
you
Moses seat. Right. So they have this authority handed down for Moses. And so notice Chris
is do and observe whatever they tell you. Yeah. Not the stuff you agree with or what seems
right to you or what you think is in accordance with the law. Whatever. Right. If they tell
you, it is not lawful to walk more than a certain distance on the Sabbath. Don't walk
more than that distance on the seven.
He says that to it, not just to his disciples, but to all the crowds that are following him.
Right. Now he says, don't do what they do because they preach, but do not practice. But when they make
these rulings, he is saying the Pharisees have these authority, the authority to make these rulings,
that these rulings are binding at this point.
All right.
Continuing on with verse four, they tie up heavy burdens hard to bear and lay them on people's
shoulders, but they themselves are not willing to move them with their finger. They do other deeds
to be seen by others, for they make their factories broad and their friends just long, and they love
the place of honor at feasts and the best seats in the synagogues and greetings in the market places
and being called rabbi by others. But you are not to be called rabbi, for you have one teacher,
and you're all
brothers and call no man your father on earth for you have one father who is in heaven.
Neither be called instructors, for you have one instructor, the Christ.
Right. And instructor there is teacher.
Teacher. Yeah. Right. So this of course, you know, we're not totally germane,
but we're just we're just pausing here because of course there are people who
It seems like this is the only verse of the New Testament they know by heart.
Uh, yes, maybe that just does have a priest. So I have this here and all the time.
This is the verse that forbids the celebration of Father's Day.
Yes. Celebrating Father's Day.
It shouldn't be calling anybody your father.
How dare you.
Yeah. Um, are you very reverend doctor?
It shouldn't be called doctor because that's the point where that's where this is going.
Teacher, so you get that. They know that one. You're not supposed to call anyone father.
But I have literally heard this lecture from Protestant...
teachers who are doctor so and so. Doc Horus in Latin is the word for teacher. Yeah. So they're
literally complaining about verse nine. Oh, how dare you be called Father Stephen. Yeah.
When verse 10 says you shouldn't be calling yourself doctor, whatever, if we're going to read it the same way.
Right? Right? But is that really what Christ is concerned about?
But I mean, does that make sense if we stop and think about it for a minute?
It's sort of a weird, yeah, it's like a weird non sequitur.
Like you could call it just those two words, too, right?
Like father and teacher are out.
Yeah.
But King is cruel and, you know, emperor and yes.
So in the Dutch tradition, in the Dutch tradition, ministers refer to as domini and then
their last name.
Master.
That don't even mean Laura
or master but that's fine because Jesus didn't say you can't call people that.
Yeah.
Let's you know, call them father or teacher. You know, you can call them lord.
You can call them master. You can call them sire. You can call them right. Like,
are you, is anyone serious in taking that interpretation that Jesus was just concerned about
these two titles because rabbi means teacher also, right? So he's just concerned about those two
time.
That's it. All other titles are good. Right. You can call yourself the grand moofty. You can call yourself whatever
But just not father or teacher
Obviously, that's not what it's talking about if you read when we read the context right we just saw the context
Of them like to make a big show in public places and make people make a big show of respect to them
Right
That this is about not
not ascribing a bunch of titles to yourself and lording it over people.
right. But there are folks who are just going to jump up and down on verse nine who me referring
to myself as the very Reverend Dr. Stephen D Young PhD, totally cool, but somebody calling me
Father Steve. How dare you? And on your Twitch stream, no less. Yes. How dare you, sir? Right.
You why are you exulting yourself with that title, Father Steve?
as opposed to the very revered Dr. Steven D. F. H. C. Whatever.
Right. Like it doesn't make sense. The dog don't hunt.
Never mind the fact that St. Paul says he's the father of the
Corinthians. Yeah, lots of people are called fathers.
And but you know, I guess St. Paul was sitting winning. Yeah.
Yeah, we did that in Corinthians. Okay. But say on verse 11,
the greatest among you should be your servant whoever exalts
himself will be humbled and whoever humbles himself will be
exalted but wo2
you scribes and Pharisees hypocrites,
for you shut the kingdom of heaven in people's faces,
for you neither enter yourselves
nor allow those who would enter to go in.
So pause it there.
You know, you've heard this probably,
especially Orthodox people have heard this
during a holy week every year, right?
And you've probably read it and heard it other times,
right? And even if you're not Orthodox.
Have you ever stopped and thought about that?
How could the Pharisees shut the door
the kingdom of heaven.
How could the Pharisees not allow someone to get into the kingdom of heaven?
Hmm.
Because they had the authority to bind into loose.
That's how.
That's how it's like it's like they had the keys to the door or something.
How about that?
Okay, verse 15, woe to use scribes and Pharisees hypocrites.
for you travel across sea and land to make a single
proselyte and people, it's not proselyte.
It's not proselyte.
And when he becomes a proselyte, you make him twice as much
a child of hell as yourselves.
Double hellian.
I like that they changed it to child of hell instead of son of hell.
So we have to be more inclusive people.
Yeah. Yeah.
What do you have?
Hell out there too.
Not to our Pharisees, but anyway.
Well, I mean, in North tradition, uh, the devil herself is, uh,
that is female.
Woe to you blind guides who say, if anyone swears by the pimple, it is nothing, but if anyone
swears by the gold of the temple, he is bound by his oath.
You blind fools from which he is greater?
The Gold of the temple, that has made the Gold sacred.
And you say, if anyone swears by the altar it is nothing but, if anyone swears by the gift
that is on the altar, he is bound by his oath.
You blind man from which is greater.
The gift or the altar that makes the gift sacred.
So whoever swears by the altar swears by it and by everything on it, and whoever swears
whoever's who-
by the temple, swears by in it and by him who dwells in it. And whoever swears by heaven,
swears by the throne of God and by him who sits upon it, woe to you scribes and Pharisees,
hypocrites, for you tithe, mint and dill and cumin, and have neglected the weedier matters of the
law, justice and mercy and faithfulness. These you ought to have done without neglecting the others.
Yeah, so let's pause there again. So price is saying look you
go and you tie, you take a 10th from your herb garden, right? You sit there like you're
trimming a little bonsai tree, right? And you, right, get these little herbs. You're so
fastidious about this, right? But things like justice, mercy, faithfulness, those you don't
see them all that concerned about, right? But notice what Jesus responses. Jesus responses
not. Those are the important things who cares about your herb garden.
Right? That's not what he says. He doesn't say you need stop making up these silly rules. God doesn't care about them.
He says you should tie from your herb garden, but not to the neglect of these other things.
Right. Not to the neglect of these other things. Yeah. So again, he's not condemning.
Right? You could go through the Torah front to back. There's nothing in there saying you need to tie from your herb garden.
This is a quote unquote rule the Pharisees added. This is an interpretation and application of the laws of tithing.
The commandments regarding tithing. Yeah. And he's here backing that up. Right. And Christ is saying that interpretation.
The application is authoritative. He's not saying, oh, that's not spelled out in the Torah. How dare you?
Yeah, because they sit on the seat of Moses.
Right.
Yeah.
All right.
Picking up with verse 24, you blind guides, straining out an ad and swallowing a camel.
Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites.
For you clean the outside of the cup in the plate, but inside, they are full of greed and
self-indulgence.
You blind Pharisee.
First clean the inside of the cup and the plate that the outside also may be clean.
to use scribes and Pharisees hypocrites for you like whitewash
tombs which outwardly appear beautiful, but within are full of dead people's bones and
all uncleanness.
So you also outwardly appear righteous to others, but within you are full of hypocrisy and
lawlessness.
Woe to you scribes and Pharisees hypocrites for you build the tombs of the prophets and
decorate the monuments of the righteous, saying, if we had lived in the days of our fathers,
we would not have taken part with them in shutting the blood of the prophets.
Thus you witness against yourselves that you are the sons of those who murdered the prophets.
up then.
measure of your fathers. You serpents, you brutive vipers, how are you to escape being
sentenced to hell? Therefore I send you prophets and wise men and scribes, some of whom you
will kill and crucify, and some you will flog in your synagogues and persecute from
town to town, so that on you may come all the righteous blood shed on earth, from the
blood of righteous able to the blood of Zachariah, the Son of Barakaya, whom you murdered
between the sanctuary and the altar. Truly I say to you all these things will come upon
this generation. O Jerusalem, Jerusalem!
a city that kills the prophets and stones those who are sent to it.
How often would I have gathered your children together as a hen gathers her
brood under her wings and you are not willing. See your house is left to you
desolate. If I tell you, you will not see me again until you say,
blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord.
So that whole last section he talks about them having murdered the prophets in the past.
Right.
What's that about? That's not just about oh you like killing people right the prophets the people who God gave that authority to in the past they killed
Right this is talking about rebellion right and he says then I'm going to send you
You.
Profits and wise men.
Right?
He's going to say
to people with authority to them. And they're not going to listen to them either. Right? They're
going to kill them. They're going to stone them. They're going to beat them in the synagogue. Right.
That's what's going to happen, right? Because the charge of being a hypocrite against the Pharisees
is that they are sort of as a person rebelling against the authority that
that God gave to them.
God gives them the authority to make rulings,
they make rulings and then don't follow their own rulings.
Right?
That's what hypocrisy ultimately is.
It's sort of a bizarre self-repelling on their part.
Right?
And so certainly, when someone else with that authority
comes to them and tells them to do something
that they don't like, they're certainly
If they rebel against their own.
authority, they'll certainly rebel against it when it comes from someone else. Right?
Right. So notice all through that. This is excoriating the Pharisees, right? But nowhere in
there, this Christ and I, but rather everywhere, all through that is He's chewing them out.
affirms that they actually have this authority.
Yeah, it's interesting.
There's a couple of comments in our YouTube chat that are basically saying almost the opposite
of this.
Like, well, they are misinterpreting, so you shouldn't.
But again, read the whole chapter, folks.
There's nowhere where Jesus says you guys are not authoritative because you're interpreting
it wrong.
Do and observe whatever they tell you.
Yeah, they are the interpreters.
They're do and observe whatever they tell you.
Yeah, this is not democracy.
It's just not.
Yeah, right.
right? Yeah. Yeah. Christ says that. Yeah. So it is not oh, they're interpreting the
Torah wrongs. So don't follow it. Christ says the exact opposite here. Yeah, it's not,
you know, as yes, they may be, but as long you're bound by it because they have the authority.
Yeah. It's not as long as you agree with them, obey them, because that's not what obedience
is. No, that's doing what you want. That's, that is, that is what the scripture calls.
man did what was r-
in his own eyes. Right, right. Which is how the Bible expresses anarchy and wicked. Yes. Yes.
There's a way that seems right to abandon it's destruction as we talked about last time. Right. Yeah.
Okay. Moving on. Oh, this is where we get the woe to you. Christ is... Let me put an even fighter
point on it. Yeah. Where does it end up? Christ is literally saying to the Pharisees,
you Pharisees are going to
go to hell for not obeying the Pharisees. Yeah. That's the charge of hypocrisy. That's
what Christ is literally saying. Yeah, they're not obeying their own words. And very clearly
saying, right? They don't do it. That's why they're heading for hell. Yeah. Because if you
outside of the cup, it didn't look nice. But inside. Yeah. If you if you interpret it
the other way, that's suggest.
that the Pharisees are actually being obedient to the law, but they're chilling everyone else not to be.
Which is the opposite of what Christ says.
Yeah. Yeah.
It takes back to those other way.
That's the exact opposite.
Yep.
So I mean, I know this isn't the way you've maybe been taught it in the past, but I mean, we're literally just reading it.
I mean, we're not, we're not quoting a bunch of church fathers interpreting it in some allegorical way.
We're just reading it.
This isn't an unclear passage.
This is a very clear and direct passage in what it is to say.
The version of this in St. Luke's Gospel is in chapter 11,
something we breathed over in the Matthew one that we'll highlight in the Luke.
The Luke 11 is the same, big content basically just kind of condensed.
But just to you know, it's not doubling down at this point. It's probably
droopling down. But verse 46 in Luke 11. Yeah. Yeah. It says, and he said, this is Jesus,
woe to you lawyers also, for you load people with burdens hard to bear and you yourselves
do not touch the burdens with one of your fingers. Yeah. So interesting. He says there,
in verse 45, it's actually kind of interesting. They, they, this isn't just lawyers catching
and they bring it on themselves.
Like in verse 45, leading up to verse 45.
Christ is saying all this stuff to the Pharisees and then these teachers of the law who are there with the Pharisees are like
What you're saying would seem to apply to us also
Right
And Christ responds at verse 46 is whoa to you too, right?
Like to go after them too, right?
Just make it clear. Yes, this does apply to you, but notice you load people with burdens hard to bear and you yourself
to not touch the burns with one of your fingers.
Does it say you low-
them with burdens and make it difficult for them.
Doesn't say you load them with burdens and they should ignore you and those burdens you're putting
on them. Right? Christ is condemning them because he says you're loading people with burdens
and then not lifting them. Right? You're doing a lot of binding and no losing. Yeah.
Right? He's criticizing them for...
how they use the authority they've been given.
Crisis pronouncing judgment against the people who have been given this authority
because they're misusing it, but the fact that they're misusing it doesn't mean they don't have it.
Right? Just like Pontius Pilate misuses his authority, but he had it.
You could say to him like, oh, you're misusing your authority.
You're not really the governor.
No, he was really the Roman governor.
Right? This is the same thing. No, the Pharisees have this authority. They're and they're
misusing it. That doesn't mean they don't have it. They're misusing what they have. What
God has given them and they're going to be held accountable for it. There's judgment
coming against them for it. So another place. Matthew 21. Now this now understanding what's
going on in Matthew 21. The big problem here is really
that this isn't a criticism of our
electionary, right? Because our
electionary has to be sort of the
way it is, right? We can't read a
whole gospel right front to back
every liturgy, right? So we've got to
take it in chunks and pieces, right?
And we cycle through and we read the
whole gospel, but it's it's taken in
pieces. But sometimes because
especially especially if we don't
go to church
every day and therefore maybe don't do the gospel reading every single day, like we're kind
of supposed to. Um, we kind of lose the flow, right? We just think about these individual
parables individually, you know, and we don't think about like, Oh, this parable is part of
a sequence of parables in the gospel. That's why it's good to just sit down and read like multiple
chapters at once. Or if you can't vote or vote books at once. Yeah, you've got to understand
parts but you've also got to
understand the whole, you've got to get both. And we get a lot of one through the daily
readings if we do them, we don't always get the big picture stuff, right? And so the
beginning of Matthew 21, we get a couple of parables, we get the parable of the prodigal
sun, and then we get the parable of the vineyard with the evil tenants, right? So parable of the
The prodigal son, most of us probably have an understanding that the the
older brother kind of represents the Jewish leaders or the Pharisees, right?
We kind of have that idea. But a lot of times when the
parable of the vineyard is taught, which is where the owner of the vineyard
lets out the vineyard to tenants and the tenants sort of refused to send the
money back and so he sends messengers there and they kill the messengers, then he
sends his son and they kill his son and then he wipes him all out and gives
You
you're just somebody else, right? Usually when that's taught, if you're in a church where they have
the guts to teach it these days, they act like it's about the Jewish people and it's about the
temple and the land and the Romans coming after Jesus is killed, right? That's not totally off-base,
but if you actually read it, especially if you read the end, right, the culmination.
Right? Because after that parable, Christ says, therefore, meaning he's about to tell us
what he's getting at and what this means. Yeah, right.
After all that, Matthew 21, starting with verse 43, therefore I tell you, the kingdom of
God will be taken away from you and given to a people producing its fruits. And the one
who falls on this stone will be broken to pieces and when it falls on anyone, it will crush
on the cheap
priests and the Pharisees heard his parables, they perceived that he was speaking about them.
And although they were seeking to arrest him, they feared the crowds because they held
him to be a prophet.
Right.
So the crowds, the people, the Judean people, do not take this to be about them.
Yeah.
And the text here is that telling us that it's about them.
This is not about taking it from the Jews and giving it to the Gentiles.
Right.
This is about the leaders.
This is about the Pharisees and the chief priests.
This is about the Sanhedrin and the chief priests.
This is about the people who have that authority that's been handed down from Moses.
That's what Christ is saying is going to be taken away from them because of their misuse
of it.
Not only is Christ saying that individually you're going to be judged for what you did with
see you.
God gave you, right, as a person, right? But as a collective, that authority is going to be taken
away from you. That chain leading from Moses to you is going to get broken. Yeah. And not to be
the dead horse too much here, but also worth pointing out that even as he's doing this, he never tells
people generally, you don't have to obey these people who currently have this authority. Yes.
Stop been taking sacrifices to the temple.
Yeah, he never says that.
Don't go to the temple to pray.
In fact, Christ goes to the temple.
Right.
Yeah, even though it's run by the Sadducees.
He pays the temple tax, even though it's a completely corrupt system.
Yeah.
Right.
He doesn't tell them don't pay the temple tax.
He doesn't tell them don't listen to the Pharisees.
He doesn't say don't do what the Pharisees tell you to do.
He says the opposite.
Right.
He never says any of that.
So what Christ is
You
talking about here, what he's saying is going to happen in terms of those chains ending,
in terms of that authority going away happens historically, not just from a Christian perspective.
From from a Jewish, you could look this up, look this up in Jewish purely Jewish resources,
okay? And you will find this out. So now a piece of this is
is the
Roman de-judification project in Palestine, right?
The province of Judea becomes the province of Palestine
in the Roman Empire after the Barcoclaire rebellion, right?
And this isn't just the temple's been destroyed.
It's, you know, Jerusalem gets leveled
and rebuilt by Hadrian.
The, the,
Jews are driven out of the city of Jerusalem.
Synagogues are destroyed all over the place.
reason we have so many first century synagogues in Galilee and Judea preserved archaeologically
is because the Romans wiped them out in the first century.
Yeah.
Cloud them under, right?
So they have this brutal de-judification process.
And part of that was it was illegal to perform an ordination, to perform the right of laying
on hands because they were trying to destroy the Sanhedrin, right?
Thank you.
already got rid of the Herodian dynasty, right? They had already got rid of effectively
the Sadducey and Chief Priest because they destroyed the temple. They also went after the
Pharisees, right? They also went after the Sanhedrin. And one of their ways to do that was
outlying the ordination. So already you start getting breaks in some of those chains because
we don't have the regular process anymore, right? Of the Sanhedrin sort of ordaining replacement
Remember.
as they lost members, for example, right?
Yeah.
And the different levels of ordination.
And the people who we read about being scribes
or teachers of the law who are sort of in training,
right?
All of that gets kind of mangled, right?
And becomes very difficult because of the Romans.
And some of those lines already get tenuous.
And then there's a shift in the second century
where a couple of things happen.
The first thing that happens is,
and the first one is because of.
just the realities of you don't have a Sanhedrin in Jerusalem anymore, right?
And so rather than the ordinations taking place through that,
the laying on of hands and the passing of authority taking place through that,
it becomes the sort of the sole prerogative of the head of a school or the head of a family,
right, to sort of choose an individual successor.
So you start seeing there
This was already true before this, but even more after this, you get lines of rabbis that are like father, son, grandson, right?
Because it's going down through the family or sort of schools where they're studying Torah and it's going from, right, the head of the school to the next head of the school.
Right.
So you have a different situation.
And in the context of that change, the actual laying on of hands part goes away.
Before that, when the doggies we have the second temple period and stuff that's preserved
in the Jerusalem Talmud and stuff from this early period, they had a basic understanding
within Judaism that this laying on of hands communicated grace and authority to the
person on whom the hands were laid, which is what we would call sacramental ordination.
Sorry Protestants.
That's in pre-Christian Judaism.
And the reason it's the right of the laying on of hands,
and this particular understanding of it, goes away in Judaism,
is because Christians had taken it over.
Christians were doing it.
And so because the Christians had kind of taken it over,
this is one of those areas where the non-Christian Jewish communities distance themselves
from Christian community.
right? We're not like them. Yeah, so this is a place. So that actual physical part of the right. So
when does do these ordinations actually stop? They come to an end. These chains that were traced all
the way back to Moses come to an end somewhere between the year 360 AD and 425 AD.
And this is part of the story of
Christianity and Judaism separating as we already noted, right? But we know they're gone by 425.
We know by 425, chain has been broken, right? Those kind of
four nations are no longer happening. So why do we say somewhere between 360 and there? Well,
In 361, a very prominent rabbi standardized the Jewish calendar going for.
forward. What was it before that? So previous to that, the San
Hadron, the religious authorities, the chief rabbis, set
the date of Pascha, the date of Passover, every year. And when
in one of those extra months was going to be added, because it
was a lunar calendar, they added it and said how many days it
would be. That was done in real time by the religious
authorities.
Right yeah, but by the time you get to 360
These or nation chains have become
the Shmikha right in Hebrew have become sort of so tenuous
that
there's
As these pro as this problem that rabbi some others are looking around
There's not a clear cut authority to keep doing it every year
There's not a clear kind of authority whoever...
everybody recognizes throughout the Jewish diaspora to do this every year.
And so the decision is made, well, we need to sort of standardize this going forward until the end
of time so that there's no ambiguity about it because they kind of realize those chains were
dying. And that happens in 361. So somewhere between 360, when it's noticed that, oh, this is all
kind of falling apart and 425 where it's fallen apart, it falls apart.
And this is in the period between 360 and 425, before the Babylonian Talmud kind of all
comes together, right?
So picking out exact dates where a lot of these things happen is tricky.
That's why we have a range, right?
And it's a kind of a large range.
And so the kinds of ordinations that were practiced from Moses until that time have not been
practice since then.
within Judaism. And there have been a few attempts at different points in history,
in different Jewish communities, in different areas, to try to revive them, to try to sort of
do archaeology and genealogy and try to, well, you know, hey, this rabbi was, you know,
a disciple of this guy who was a disciple of that guy, and try and trace it back and try and
They've never been widely acclaimed or reckoned.
recognized enough to sort of start it back up.
And so to this day, there is rabbinical ordination,
but it is very much.
And any Jewish source will tell you this,
not the same thing.
So someone who has made a rabbi now after finishing,
they go to Jewish theological seminary
if they reform or they study in a particular place
to be orthodox or part of another group, right?
Jewish.
They get in ordination, they're made a rabbi, they recognize as a rabbi, but there's not
someone who has the kind of authority that say a gemalial did who could trace that authority
back to Moses and whose rulings are sort of always final.
Right?
There are rabbis who gain good reputation who have sort of charismatic levels of authority
above other rabbis of that kind of thing, but there's not a pope of the Jew.
right? There's not a there's not sort of one person or even a group right like a
Sanhedrin like a recognized group that all the Jewish people in the world
recognize is having this authority for Moses and their rulings are sort of
final yeah right yep and so any given rabbis opinion more
negotiable or more provisional. Some scholars say right.
And so there's a lot more arguments and different viewpoints and that kind of thing.
And that's, you know, I'm sure from a Jewish perspective, that's not a bad thing.
Right?
That's, yeah, they're very smart to that.
But it is a change, right?
It is a change.
And what we're going to talk about here now in the second half is, as we've already mentioned here,
the way in which Christianity carries on the original mode of understanding of
or
in succession.
Yep.
All right, we're going to go ahead and take our first break and we'll be right back
with the second half of this episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take
your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation of
the epistles of Saint Paul, disconnected from any historical reality.
The Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish
world.
In Saint Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations, Father Stephen D. Young surveyes
Paul's life in writings, interpreting them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox
church.
is followed by the youngs.
Interpretive translation of St. Paul's Epistles, which deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in 1st century Judaism,
DeYoung hopes to unsettle commonly held notions and help the reader reassess St. Paul
in his historical context. Available now at store.AncientFaith.com. Again, that is store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father-
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
Before we take a couple calls,
I just want to give a little brief advertisement.
We've sold out all the rooms at the Antioch in Village
for the Lord of Spirits Conference.
However, there are still lots of commuter tickets available.
And I think there's still a weeding list.
you'd like to try your chance to get one of the rooms at the village. But if you can't get one
of those rooms, you can get a room somewhere else in the area. There are places to go so you can go
to store.AncientFaith.com slash events to get your tickets. The Lord of Spirits conference is the
first weekend in October of this year at the Antioch in Village. So it's going to be a lot of fun.
We're going to have... I know that we're going to have a tournament playing the Royal Game of
or there's going to be...
couple of surprises. Father Steven has assured me he's not going to throw rotten vegetables
at the crowd like he did last time. Just, you know, in a show of inversion or whatever.
But there's people who need lodging. There's an abandoned house near an old graveyard, about
150 yards from the village. So if you want to squat there.
There you go.
Feel free.
So, all right, well, we do have some collars.
So we very patiently have William from Tennessee.
He's been waiting all of this time.
He called like right after the show started.
So this guy is very serious.
So was he bored on top there?
Good old Rocky top probably.
William, welcome to the Lord of Spheres podcast.
Thank you.
Can you hear me dominate Andrew and Vera Reverend Dr. Stephen?
We hear you.
Yes.
You should call him Dominie.
He's the Dutch guy.
You know, Father Stephen has made that same Born on a Mountain Top in Tennessee multiple
times and I've called in.
Maybe I should say I'm from Kentucky or something.
Wow.
Is this...
If nothing else.
Indeed.
What's up?
I have two questions, both of them on Apostolic Succession and it's continuity with the
State of Moses.
My first question goes back to the episodes of World of Priests Craft and Profit Motive,
distinction was made between priestly roles and
prophetic roles where the prophetic role represents God to men and priestly roles
represents men to God. In a role of priestcraft, you mentioned the priestly role in
prophet role while ideally unified were splits at the time of Moses between the
priestly role of Aaron and the prophetic role of Moses, which suggested the
authority of the seat of Moses was slash is prophetic and potentially distinct
from the priestly authority.
So my first question is cheating because
It actually has parts A, B and C, but hopefully part NB
have monolexical answers.
So 1A is the authority of the seat of Moses prophetic
priestly or both.
1B is the authority of apostolic succession,
prophetic priestly or both.
And 1C, if they do have prophetic and or priestly authority,
how do you understand the authority of these priests
profits coming from this ordination of life.
on of hand as distinct and interacting with the authority of profit and priests who
do not have this, such as the priest Aaron, the prophet of Deborah or Saint Matron of the
Blind.
So it's one A B and C. I was getting a little lost with all of the sub questions there.
Did you catch that all?
I did.
I followed.
Okay.
All right.
So, so, uh, in terms of Moses, we're talking about prophetic authority and it's distinct from
priestly authority, right? So it's like in the what text we read in the Gospels, it's the chief
priest and the Pharisees realize he's talking about them, right? Those are sort of the two pieces
of the leadership, right? Group together is the shepherds of Israel, often in like Ezekiel when
God is condemning them. In the case
of the apostles at Apostolic succession,
which we're gonna turn to now,
there those roles are recombined.
Yeah, yeah.
And they're recombined based on a couple of things.
One of them being Pentecost
and the Holy Spirit and the relationship
with the Holy Spirit to the prophetic role.
The other one being that the
The New Testament priesthood is a different priesthood.
It is not the eronic Levite priesthood,
the Loventical priesthood, right, and C. Hebrews, right.
It is sharing and participating in the,
so the priesthood, Father Andrew and I have,
is a participation at a certain degree in the priesthood
Christ who was not a Levi.
who was not descended from Aaron.
Right.
And Hebrews deals with that sort of at link.
But that's the purpose of the figure of Melchizedek,
that the figure of Melchizedek plays,
which he brings in through Psalm 110,
to apply to Christ in his priesthood.
So then, third question was
about people who did not have per se ordination
but I played a...
a role, if I remember you right?
It seems right.
Can we confirm?
Is that right William?
That's right.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, that's something we actually see in the Old Testament, too.
Right.
So, for example, Deborah in judges.
Has not received the laying on of hands.
Right.
Pastown for Moses.
has this
but has this prophetic role, sort of directly, directly from God, right?
And so this is a case of God is not bound by his own rules.
Right, we're bound by God's rules. God isn't bound by his rules.
So just like we have martyrs who were never baptized.
water in a church. And that doesn't mean, oh, baptism is the correct way for someone to
be received in the church and receive remission of sins. There are people who God gives authority
to and reveals himself to directly in non-normal cases. But that doesn't affect the normal
case, right? You don't argue from the abnormal case to the normal
case. You don't say as some do, unfortunately, well, look, the thief on the cross next to
Christ was it baptized and went to paradise. Therefore, baptism is an important or is
unnecessary. These things don't set presidencies. Right. And the correct response to that is,
well, yes, if you are ever being crucified next to our Lord, you don't have to be baptized.
Anyway.
you today you'll be with me in paradise you're good right right so so Christ is God right has
authority that sort of sort of supervings that and so there are these exceptional cases but the
normal case right the normal case the way God normally operates with us is that this authority is
passed down through ordination.
Yeah, I mean another example of...
I'm...
of this sort of thing that's actually,
that is very directly your main tour discussing is
where the scribes and the Pharisees will criticize Jesus
because of things that he chooses to do on the Sabbath.
They'll say, you know, our rulings say,
you should not do this.
But it's, and Jesus never says,
now everybody, you know, you don't have to obey them anymore.
But rather he says, look, I'm the Lord of the Sabbath.
So in other words, my rulings supersede yours.
Right, he has superior authority.
Right.
He can.
make rulings as to what's appropriate for him to do on the Sabbath.
Right. But he never tells other people, oh, just ignore them.
Yeah, never, never. Yep. So all right. Thank you very much for calling William. Good to talk to you.
All right. We're going to move on to our next caller. And that is Brian calling from Virginia. So
Brian, welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast.
Thanks, fathers.
I've always wanted to greet.
you from Virginia, Father. Yes, the Holy Land, the old dominion looks like a turkey on its belly
or a chicken on its back. My question is about Matthew 15. So here it seems like the Pharisees are
criticizing Jesus' disciples for not following this tradition of washing their hands when they eat.
And I was curious from from what you were talking about earlier just
how to make what y'all were talking about fit with that.
Yeah, so is this one of those cases, Father,
where Jesus has basically told his disciples,
this is what I expect of you?
Or, I mean, how does this work?
Do you think Jesus didn't want them to wash their hands
before they ate?
I mean, that's kind of a good idea.
Ferrisis aside.
Yeah.
But he doesn't even defend them for that.
I'm trying to remember now exactly.
Well, no, what he does is he turns that around
on the Pharisees.
Yeah, right.
And it's another thing like the uti of Minton, Dillon, Cuman, right?
And the point he makes, so he really makes a very technical point about the law there
that even a person who eats an unclean animal is not technically made unclean themselves
by it.
Yeah.
They have sinned by violating a commandment, right?
But they haven't...
contracted so in cleanness, whereas what comes out of a person, literally bodily secretions
does make a person ceremonially unclean.
But then Christ analogizes from that back to the Pharisees, right?
Instead of talking about bodily secretions, talking about what comes out of your mouth in terms
of speech, right?
In terms of right.
And what you do, right?
And so it's a criticism of the fair...
he's saying, okay, yeah, this is another case where you're concerned about these very concerned about these outward things.
He's not saying don't wash your hands before you eat, right? Like no, it's ever interpreted that way that I know of that Christians ought not to watch their hands before they.
Right, because of this passage.
But, right, but that you should be even more concerned about these other more serious things.
right and he's talking to the people who are talking to
him in particular. He's not talking about abstract Pharisees. He's talking to Christ
knows the individual people because he created them who are talking to him at that moment.
And he's saying, you bob the Pharisee and Tim the Pharisee, right? You need to be more
concerned about this, right? You need to be more concerned about this. So this is like an
and Intincument Thing.
Right, and there's also,
so there's another element here.
in terms of rabbinical interpretation too, where the way in which they're publicly calling
out Jesus disciples, subjecting someone to that kind of public humiliation is something
that's forbidden to those in authority.
There's a level of that too.
Yeah, I mean, Christ is correcting.
Judging another man's servant kind of thing.
Right.
Yeah.
which I mean until and then the and when the internet
was invented, then you can judge everyone else's servant and their masters.
Yeah, that's cool.
But but I don't see how you can read that and get out of it.
That what Jesus is saying is, you know, don't listen to those Pharisees eat without washing
your hands.
Yeah.
Yeah, I don't think that's a viable interpretation.
Is that clear, Brian?
Yeah.
Thank you.
Great.
All right.
Thank you very much for calling.
we're gonna take one more call before.
we roll on and we have Caleb calling from Michigan. Are you calling for Michigan, Caleb?
No, I am calling from the upper peninsula. Oh, you don't consider that. Well, are you
going to say no to Michigan? I don't know. He's a uper, but apparently considers that
to be a separate entity. Don't even consider the trolls your company, your countrymen,
I guess. No, I consider them like North Ohio.
Oh wow wow yeah that was a different yeah well what's on your mind Caleb from the UP?
My question is a bit of a delicate question because there are so many people that have been harmed by
divorce and coming from I was a conservative anabaptist before I was brought into the church a few
year of sickle.
And in Matthew 19, Christ gets asked questions about divorce.
Is it okay to divorce our wives for just any reason?
And he says, you know, having not read,
that God created them a male and female,
and that they should come together and become one flesh.
And they say, well, then why did Moses give us the ability
to write out a rid of divorce?
I just really listen to Dr. Aronomi.
I was kind of interesting, but he said because of the hardness of your hurts, but from the beginning, it was not so.
And when I'm having discussions with extended family or friends, this one always comes up.
And I try to explain that the church's position on this is a little bit more nuanced than just allowing divorce.
But it is a very difficult question.
I would love to hear a whole show on this.
But particular to this series or these two episodes, what is going on there authority-wise?
For Christ was saying, yes, Moses told you this, but that.
So what do you think, Father? Is this a Moses said this, but that? Is he changing what Moses said?
No, I mean, Christ obviously is pointing out the original created intent with God created the world,
Right, there would not be divorce. That's the two, right? As he says the two would become
one flash and had be together forever.
That was the original sort of intent behind marriage.
But, right, notice Christ doesn't say
Moses was wrong, or all of you who did what Moses said
were actually sinning.
Hmm, right?
Moses had the authority to make that judgment call.
Christ is not denying that.
He's next.
complaining why, right?
That he said, you know, he looked at you people,
he saw how hard your hearts were, right?
And he made a concession basically.
He made a ruling that was a concession to your weakness.
But he put some boundaries around it saying,
right, you can't just throw her out.
You can't just abandon her, right?
Yeah, you have to, you have to give her a rid of divorce,
right?
And of course, at that time, you know,
They were abusing that.
session. I did too. Like, oh, it's okay. I can divorce her for any reason as long as I give her a rid of divorce, right?
Which also I'm pretty sure isn't what Moses intended, right when he made that concession. Yeah, right.
And this really carries over into the church's practice regarding divorce.
Right, which is we all acknowledge it's a bad thing. The church doesn't give divorces the church pendants as divorces,
meaning
The church helps people who have been harmed and damaged by going through a divorce helps
them heal and be reintegrated into the community and come close to God again.
That's what the church does, right?
Now there's some other folks out there, based in Italy, who will say, oh no, we don't allow
divorce but if you give it up money to your low
bishop you can get an enolment where we say that you were never married and all your kids are illegitimate.
Yeah, all you did was fornicate.
So we create this elaborate fiction and pretend that no divorce happened.
What's the problem with that?
Well, there's no healing in that for anyone.
Yeah.
It's a nice legal dodge, right?
And it helps your apologists score points by saying they don't they don't allow divorce.
But you're not actually helping anyone enter the kingdom of heaven.
them because you're not helping anyone heal. You're not helping anyone grow and you're not
helping the situation. Right. So the the same thing and anybody who has a problem with the church
allowing people to have a second marriage, go read the service of second marriage. I've done one.
Yeah. Me too. Okay. When you're standing there doing one and you're literally reading St. Paul saying,
you know, well, we're basically here because it's better for you to marry than to burn with lust
in a public wedding ceremony, right?
You get the drift, right? We're not saying, oh, this is fine.
Yeah. Right. We're saying, look, this is the real world.
Bad things happen. People have hard hearts.
We're not in the ideal world.
We're in a simple world. And so we've got to do the best we can.
And the people who have the authority to bind into loose,
to allow things and not allow things, right?
Right. Those people have
to use that authority to try to help people enter the kingdom of heaven.
Because that's what Christ is condemning the Pharisees for.
All through that chapter we read, right?
You're supposed to be trying to help people enter into the kingdom
and instead you're stopping them.
You're making it harder, you're blocking the door, you're burdening them down.
And not lightning their load, right?
So you're doing the exact opposite of what you're supposed to be doing with your authority.
But shepard
someone to the toward the kingdom requires both mercy and discipline. That's why we get called father because it's like parenting a child. Right? You have to have mercy and discipline and no when to apply which
in order to help guide them to where they need to be. Yeah.
Alright, well, thanks for calling Caleb and greetings to all the Hoosers up there.
Yep.
peninsula of Michigan.
All right.
I would love to, you know, one of one of the bishops of our archdioceses from Iron Mountain actually,
Bishop Anthony.
He's a uper.
Yes, I know, I know Bishop Anthony.
Yeah, he got, he got stolen from us.
Alas, Alas.
I have a former resident too.
Down here's a parishioner.
Oh, and boy, was that a weather shock?
That's not a good thing.
Yeah, no, literally be upper-pinitle.
Yes, yes.
All right.
Okay.
Well, here we are in the second half
of this episode of Lord of Spirits.
So, yeah, I mean, what exactly...
What exactly is it that the apostles get?
Like, what is the authority that Jesus gives to them?
Well, now we can move on
so people can stop hating on the Pharisees.
Everybody does.
I know, I know.
Hating on them Pharisees.
Yeah.
Just a lot of people are just utterly incredulous
that.
they had any kind of authority whatsoever.
Yeah, but God bless you.
It's in the Bible. Read it. Read it, fellas.
I'm not using fellows as gendered language there.
I'm using it as the the shameless sentence.
Yeah, so that change is historically, not just from a Christian
perspective, but historically gets broken.
But what we find when we
read the New Testament closely is that Christ begins a new chain. Right? Christ begins a new
ordination that's coming from him in his authority. Yeah, which, or remember, where Moses' authority
actually starts? Where does that start? That starts when Moses sees God. Right? Yeah. Yeah.
So Christ's new chain is going to start with the apostles because what did the apostles do?
They saw God.
They saw God, right?
So, so already in the Gospels, Christ is going to talk about the fact that he is going to give
this authority to his disciples and apostles. And one of the most famous places he starts talking about
that, the passage about which there is no controversy whatsoever. He's in Matthew 16 verses 13 through 20.
Yes, all right.
Matthew 16, verses 13 to 20.
Now, when Jesus came into the district of Cestoria,
Philippi, he asked his disciples,
who do people say that the Son of Man is?
And they said, some say John the Baptist,
others say Elijah, others Jeremiah,
or one of the prophets, he said to them,
but who do you say that I am?
Simon Peter replied,
you are the Christ, the Son of the living God.
And Jesus answered him.
Blessed are you, Simon Barjona, for flesh and blood has not revealed this to you, but
my Father who is in heaven.
And I tell you, your Peter, and on this rock I will build my church and the gates of
hell shall not prevail against it.
I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatever you bind on earth shall
be bound in heaven and whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven.
and he strictly charged the disciples to tell no one that he was the Christ.
So that's totally clear and uncontroversial, I'm sure.
Yeah, I mean, no one's argued about this.
This is just, this is just say, say Peter, you're the pope.
When I leave you take over.
Yeah.
No, obviously not, right?
Well, maybe not obviously, sorry, sorry, Roman Catholic listeners, right, to whom that
may actually seem obvious.
I mean, hey, you and I are, are priests of the successor of Peter.
So it was an anti-Ian problem, right?
An aunt here.
Yeah.
Yeah, say it's Peter Paul. We're in Antioch first, man. Everybody knows the reunion tour. Not as if it's the original.
That's right.
Had to be there for the original.
Um,
Right. So,
the, the, the, that we're talking about authority is putting, should be pretty clear by now.
After an episode and a half or so of this,
that this binding and losing this authority to bind into the loose.
keys of the kingdom of heaven, that door that the Pharisees were shutting in front of people.
Right? This isn't Matthew. We're within a couple chapters. All these things passages are reading
in Matthew are in one big block of text together. Right? Yeah. It seems that authority is on Jesus'
mind. Yes. Right. So this is that same authority. That same authority that the Pharisees he's condemned
for misusing. Even though he acknowledged that they legitimately had it, they've misused it.
he's told the Pharisees he's gonna take it from them and give it to someone else.
And now he's saying to say, Peter, hey, you're at least one of, right?
We'll stay open here, right?
Since we just read this one text, he's at least one of the people to whom Christ is going
to give that authority, right?
And a lot is made, of course, again, people read this text in isolation from the text around
it.
is made about the location and so we've talked about the location where
where say Peter says this and all these things, right? But do you think, hear me out here, do you think
that an understanding what verses 13 through 20 are talking about? Do you think verses 1 through 12
might be relevant? Yeah. And have we already read four of those verses tonight? Yeah. Yes we have.
Yeah, this is where they come to Jesus and say give us a sign.
Right. And then after that Christ talks about...
about the levied of the Pharisees.
Yeah, which that's their hypocrisy, right?
Their bad behavior.
They're so he's just spent what would become,
because of course the first numbers weren't there originally,
but what would become 12 verses, right?
Criticizing the Pharisees, use of their authority, right?
And that's when we get to this.
That's where we get this story.
And this story is not in the same-
place in the text in all this and up to Gospels. But here it comes right after the Pharisees.
And before some more talk about the Pharisees. So it is nested within Christ's critique
of the way in which the Pharisees have used their authority. It uses the same language
that he's used regarding the Pharisees' use of authority. He's told the Pharisees he's
taking the authority away from doing it to someone else. And now he's telling St. Peter,
I'mma give it to you.
Yeah, right and notice it's I will right
So he's not doing it right here. We say he's going to do it
Hmm at this point
Matthew 16 he's going to to give it to him
Okay
Now
We also can't neglect where the text goes. So let's go a little further in Matthew another little piece
and these couple of chapters.
We're reading all this stuff.
out of a couple of chapters, said of a few chapters in Matthew. It's going to
Matthew 18 because he's going to use that language again there. Okay, starting
with verse 15. If your brother sins against you, go and tell him his fault
between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother. But
if it does not listen, take one or two others along with you that every charge
may be established by the evidence of two or three witnesses. If he refuses to
Listen.
them, tell it to the church. And if it refuses to listen even to the church, let him be to you as a
Gentile and a tax collector. Truly, I say to you, whatever you and this is plural. So whatever
y'all bind on earth shall be bound in heaven. And whatever y'all loose on earth shall be loose in
heaven. And again, I say to y'all, if two of you agree on earth about anything they ask, it will
be done for them by my father in heaven for where two or three are gathered in my name, there am I
among them.
the correct plural is all y'all. Oh that's the pervasive plural. That means every single last one of you.
So, right. So, here's even this piece that we read gets chopped up a little, right? Like how many
times have you heard verse 20 quoted all by itself as if that's talking about worship? Yeah.
Right, whereas notice where two
or three occurs at verse 16.
Yeah, this is about making this ruling.
Two or three witnesses.
So when you act as two or three,
those of you with authority, right?
When you act as two or three,
they are acting with Christ's authority
to bind and to loose.
Okay, this is talking about...
church leadership, right? And if you don't believe it just based on that, this whole
discussion started in verse 1 of Matthew 18 when the disciples came to Jesus
saying, who is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven? Yeah. So this is part of a
discussion about how authority works in the kingdom, about how authority works in
the church.
Yeah, I mean this is basically setting up
Consilier authority like right there's certain things that that needs to be decided by authority as a group
Yes
Yeah, that when they do that and that's why the use here are all plural which tells us since this is
You know nowadays two chapters right later
Right, it's the same language, but in the plural. It's not just Saint Peter who receives that authority
Bye!
It's all of the disciples.
Yep.
Right.
And something similar in John 20.
Well, so this has all been sort of future aimed, right?
Yeah.
I will give this authority to you.
This, right, I will give this authority to you.
This is how you will handle things in the community in the future when you're leaders in
it, right?
And now as we get to John 20, we're after the resurrection.
of Christ, where between the resurrection and the ascension.
Sence.
Yeah.
Right.
And so now some of these things that Christ said he was going to do are going to start happening.
Yeah.
I mean, this to be a very familiar passage to Orthodox Christians.
This gets read at a copy of Espers right after, you know, on Paska and then also then a bigger
selection from John 20 on Thomas Sunday the Fox.
So John 20, he's starting with verse 19.
On the evening of that day, the first day of the week,
the doors being locked where the disciples were for fear of the Jews.
Jesus came and stood among them and said to them, peace be with you.
When he had said this, he showed them his hands and his side.
Then the disciples were glad when they saw the Lord.
Jesus said to them again, peace be with you as the Father has sent me,
even so I am sending you.
And when he had said this, he breathed on them and...
said to them, receive the Holy Spirit. If you forgive the sins of any, they are forgiven them.
If you withhold forgiveness from any, it is without.
All right. So this text is viewed by a lot of our Protestant friends as a problem text
because, well, wait a minute, I thought the apostles received the Holy Spirit on Pentecost.
Yeah.
No, this is not 43 days after this.
Right. This is receiving the Holy Spirit
for this ministry he is giving them.
Right. Right.
This is different. Right.
The Holy Spirit is poured out on all flesh at Pentecost.
Yeah.
C. Joel 2, which St. Peter quotes it.
This is behind closed doors with just the apostles.
This is just the apostles. Right.
This is the beginning.
This is now they have this authority.
divine and delus, that's why he uses the same language. They have now received it and it's they plural.
Yeah, y'all know a puzzle is singled out here not say Peter not the disciple whom Jesus loved who wrote it right?
It's not and none of them are singled out right? It's all of them received this authority and therefore
Each one of them represents the beginning of a chain
Each one of them is now going to become the first link in the check.
Yeah, but before we move on to that, right, when the third half we're going to talk about the
the chains continuing. What kind of authority do we see the apostles exercising it and how do they
exercise it in the New Testament? Yeah, we sort of talked about how the prophets after Moses
exercise their authority in the Old Testament.
how a lot of that is reflected in the text itself,
same as true of the New Testament.
A lot of folks don't know unless you've read my book
about it.
At Gameliel, the rabbi, St. Paul's teacher,
wrote a pistles.
We don't have the texts of them,
but it is recorded in the Talmud,
Some of the places he sent...
letters to and a sort of a summary of the context, right? Like he, contents, like he sent
a letter to this community about the date of this feast, right? Like that kind of summary,
right? But so what is, what is Cavalier doing there? Well, he is a member of the San
Hedren, somebody who has this authority is answering questions and making rulings
for different Jewish communities scattered around the world who recognize his authority
and write to him and ask him.
questions and asking for these rulings right. And St. Paul when he begins writing
epistles seems to be doing the exact same thing. Yeah, he's acting in a very rabbi kind
of way. Right. Like he's answering questions. He's making rulings on disputes that they're
having. He's correcting things. Right. He's applying things. Here's how you want to do this.
right? I mean, very practicals. Here's how people ought to dress.
Here's some people ought to act in, you know, here's how you ought to organize things, right?
Like very practical things and and part of this is again, we have to reorient ourselves with the epistles actually are
Because a lot of us have gotten this really wonky way of looking at
The if it not just say Paul's epistles, but all of the epistles from the Apostles
There's a whole vessel with a pestle joke
You know waiting to be made in here, but that may be so deep in the crates that like
Thank you.
Some of you kids have never seen a Danny K movie in its shows.
But, uh,
people have this idea that like, for example, St. Paul's
Epistle to the Romans is a systematic theology.
Sorry, Calvinus.
Uh, it's not, it's not right.
There are philosophical and theological treatises from this time
here, like, Philo wrote them.
This Jewish guy.
century before Saint Paul, right?
Saint Paul was super educated.
He could have written those if he wanted to.
For all we know, he may have written some of those, but they're not in the Bible, right?
So they're not scripture.
That's not what epistles are.
Epistles are letters to communities of people dealing with actual real-time issues, problems,
disputes, right?
that need to be taught and explained. Right?
And that's what the epistles are doing, not just St. Paul's, say James, St. Peter, St. John,
right, that's what they're all doing by these epistles.
They're making rulings, they're exercising their authority and dealing with this in the real life
right of communities, right.
And we're going to get into this one of the third half, but after the last epistle written in the New Testament.
People with authority, the church don't stop writing epistles.
That keeps writing on going, but we'll talk more about that in the third half.
The other way we see them exercising their authority, so that's basically right, acts
as narrative where we see them exercising their authority, and the rest of the Bible
is basically epistles.
Even Revelation has the letters attached to the beginning.
Right so pretty much the whole rest of the new test
is a pistillary literature, which is then first hand exercising this authority, but then in acts,
we read second-hand descriptions of them exercising this authority. And the primary way we see that
happening is conciliar authority. And that conciliar authority exhibit A is acts 15 and the council
held in Jerusalem. But even outside of that, right? I mean, that's an exhibit A because that's
everybody getting together.
Yeah. Right. Uh, formally to resolve a question, but there are all kinds of time, you know,
St. Paul visits that he meets with St. Peter, James and John. Right. Like we've seen these other episodes of the Apostles coming together and doing things together in the book of Acts. Right.
It's not just limited to to the council. We also see and there are two elements here to this conciliate. There's conciliatory, but there's also privacy.
On one hand, this authority is given to all the apostles.
On the other hand, within the operation of the apostles as a group, there are certain
figures who have primacy.
That primacy is primarily, they're at the beginning.
Later on, as you get later in the century, it's going to push more towards, for a century,
it's going to push more towards St. Peter and Paul.
the earlier phase, and especially in Jerusalem, it's St. Peter James and John.
And we see it the Gospels already Christ when he goes off by himself when he does some of his
most
unprecedented miracles like raising the dead and things
Right or when he's transfigured right he takes
St. Peter James and John right those are the ones always go with him and St. Paul is later going to call
say, Peter James had John the Pillars. Right?
which is a way of comparing them to Abraham Isaac and Jacob.
Right, so say, Peter James and John have this kind of primacy.
Here's a really interesting thing though that you may not have thought about.
The James and Acts is not the same human as the James in the Gospels.
Yeah, there's Peter, James and John, and there's Peter, different James and John.
Right, James, the set of zebadi is the one who's at the transfiguration
and sees the little girl race from the dad, right?
Oh.
these things. And it's, St. James the brother of the Lord, who's the head of the Church of
Jerusalem, who makes the final ruling at the Council of Jerusalem in Acts 15. That's
not the same person. So St. James, in the New Testament, is an office.
Yeah, weirdly.
The successor to St. James is St. James
within the New Testament.
So that already is telegraphing.
That already is sending us a signal if you're reading it closely,
if you're reading the narrative of Acts closely, because the narrative of
Acts tells us about St. James, a set of seven, he being killed by Herod.
So this is it. He's not trying to pull.
a switch of root, he tells us, oh yeah, that's St. James now who I was talking about with
St. Peter and John in the Gospel of Luke in volume one here in volume two at the beginning
he dies, but there's this other St. James who takes his place. And that privacy of those
three. Right. And so each of them has authority to make rulings and do what they're doing.
Right. And then when there are big things that affect everybody, think...
gather together. Two or three, right, or like the San
Hadron would gather, right, the elders of Israel would gather
and they make these they make these decisions together.
It's a pattern we see already with the apostles. It's
telegraphing what we're going to see because of course, the
Today's going to come, you know, as we move late into the first...
century, when we get, you know, there's only going to be one apostle left that's going
to be Saint John. By the time you get past, you know, probably 80, 80, 80 for sure. We've
only got one left of that Saint John, and by the time you get a few years into the second
century, Saint John has gone to. So in the third half, we will talk about what happens
This is an authority that Chris gave the apostles once the apostles are in a round.
any more.
All right well you've wasted another perfectly good hour so
of your life listening to Lord of Spirit's podcast we're
going to be right back with the third half see you soon.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Perhaps you are a seeker exploring the abundance of the Orthodox faith, or maybe you're a young
mother wanting to share the fullness of Orthodoxy with your children and family, or perhaps
you are single trying to find shelter from unclean images or words, or an empty nester wanting
to fill your time with edifying thoughts, prayers, discussions, and content, or maybe you feel
alone. Just want to find Solace.
and comfort. Regardless of your own unique circumstances, ancient faith radio is here to help with your orthodox journey.
Please consider partnering with us by becoming a monthly recurring donor so that we can continue our mission to spread the orthodox faith
and help support the spiritual lives of the already faithful. Any consistent donation larger small will enable us to focus on our mission on a baby.
Simply visit www.AncientFate.com slash support and start your monthly donations today.
All gifts or tax deductible.
and greatly appreciate it.
Thank you.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back.
It's the third half of the 119th episode
of Lord of Spirits podcast.
We're talking.
about apostolic succession, the authority given by God first to Moses and his
successors and now to the apostles of Jesus and their successors. So we left off
talking about the authority given to the apostles. So what happens next in this
exciting episode?
I know this is like an early episode of Lord Spirit's podcast. I call on Father
or Stevens just not even there.
I love it. It's very retro.
They help me turn my mic back on. Oh.
Should I find I find a Mexican radio station? Yeah, exactly.
We start playing that in the back. There's no calls.
We've we've pacified everyone. I yeah, I think I don't know.
I think we've either made all the people triggering everyone.
All of the anti-faircy types who are not going to buy the
the teacher that says be a Pharisee, I think they walked off angry.
So, okay, it's okay. It's all right. You're welcome. We don't go away, Matt.
Just go away. No, don't drive angry. Whatever you do. Yeah. Um, yeah. So yeah, it does not
indeed stop with the apostles. Yeah. Uh, the, uh, as we said, the apostles are the beginning,
Right of a new...
of a new chain of authority because just like we said about the Torah and about the rest of the Hebrew Bible,
believe it or not, even once we add in the New Testament writings to Scripture, there are still some questions that people have
about how to interpret and apply various things.
Yeah.
uh... rulings need to be made
yeah and let's
Right.
Protestant friends, right?
Gather in.
Right.
Not this is not a dunking on the holoscryptor thing.
I don't honestly, isn't right.
You got to admit that there's a lot of questions.
Right.
It's not.
I mean, just like not everything having to do with the Christian life, ethyology is abundantly
clear to everyone who reads the scriptures.
Right.
We all know that.
We don't have to reject the holoscryptor to say that.
Yeah, okay
you all have have preachers and commentaries and like you got people that are interpreting
and applying and making rulings too. Right. Yeah. Problem is. Problem is.
All those folks are doing it differently.
And so the issue is, right?
This is the issue faced in due to the economy by the Israelites.
Well, how do we know who the person is?
How do we know who to listen to?
Right?
If I got five guys, I'll call themselves Prophet and they're all saying different things.
How do I know who really has the authority to rule on this?
Right?
Yeah.
Well, you know, on that question, we have a caller calling from the Great White North
Thank you.
Um, in further north of the Upper Peninsula, that's correct from Ontario. Although, you know,
well, depending on where it's Ontario, that could be south. I know. I know. It's true. It's true.
That's the thing about. It's already so much of it is south of America. Yeah. It's not south America.
Um, but yes, so we have we have Dan calling from Ontario. Um, see the call board is saying
Ontario Cali like California but that can't.
Oh Ontario California that's
a whole different place. Is that really true? Yes, that's the IE. No, that's right. Dan,
are you from California? I am actually from California. Oh,
Ontario, California. Okay. You know, I grew up in Redlands, right? I do. I do. And I
know there's been a story about you and something about what I'm going to ask about that happened
I think you in Redlands. Yeah. No, Ontario, California is a real place. They had a cool
all back of the day.
I mean, I knew that there is an Ontario Ohio, but yeah, no, Ontario bills, well, they have an airport too. It was like the cheaper airport.
All right, well, Dan, I'm a little disappointed you're not from Canada, but but that's okay. I on the other hand think Ontario, California is way better than Canada. So.
All right, Dan, what is on your mind?
So I have a question and I also have a hot pick.
So my question is
is everything that you guys have described about the profits and the laying out of hands and
things like that kind of sound like a lot of what Joseph Smith said.
And where do you think he got it from?
Well, that's the thing.
I mean, was he a genius who happened to be able to know everything about the Bible and
recreated in a story.
Or did he maybe actually have it happen?
Can I start with this one, Father?
Oh no, go for it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I have a, I don't know.
I have an enduring love for Mormons.
I love Mormons.
I've been to many Mormon historical sites, including the one that is right here in Pennsylvania,
which is called the priesthood restoration site. Did you know about this?
I'm checking your LDS knowledge, Dan.
Yes, that's where Joseph Smith had a vision of I think it was it was it was a peer change in
John. So that's part of it. Yeah, you got part of it. And so yeah, they restored the
the no-calactic priesthood upon justness.
Yeah, so there's a site.
Now it's no longer called this, but back when he was up there it was called Harmony
Pennsylvania.
Now it has some kind of lame something or other township name.
But Harmony Pennsylvania up on the Susquehanna and there he and his buddy Oliver Cowdery
baptized each other in the Susquehanna.
And Joseph Smith claims that he saw Peter James and John, they gave him the Melchizedek
priesthood.
also said that he saw John the Baptist who gave him the
Aaronic priesthood and also he lived up there for a while and that's where he says that he
translated the golden plates that he got up there in upstate in New York.
And I've visited this site actually a couple of times.
And yeah, it's true that he's essentially he's reading the Bible and he's claiming to have
experiences like the apostles had or whatever but there's actually something quite
interestingly different between what he even claims, which number one I will say I do
not believe that that happened to him or that it or that whatever happened to him is
not exactly the way he interpreted it. I'll just put it that way. I'm not saying he didn't
have some kind of experiential experience, but doesn't mean it was a good one. But he
claims that he, you know, that these saints appeared to him and ordained him, right?
which is different than the way that prophecy becoming a prophecy.
it works everywhere in the Bible, which is that God directly picks you.
Now, obviously, the Mormon system works different, but that is a pretty significant difference,
even what he says about it.
Now I don't believe that Peter, James and John ordained him.
I do not believe that John the Baptist ordained him.
But yes, he's clearly drawing on these traditions and claiming them for himself.
I do recommend, I mean, you might...
well, no way more about this than I do.
But for those who don't maybe,
there's a book that I recommend reading
to get a sense of Joseph Smith.
I mean, there's a number of biographies of him.
There's actually a new one that just came out.
I can't remember the author.
But the one that I like the best is by a woman named
Fawn Brody.
And Fawn Brody was the niece of one of the profit slash
presidents of the LDS church.
And she wrote a book called No Man Knows My History,
in which you get, I think it's
It's a pretty convincing story of the life of Joseph Smith.
And you mentioned the idea of like, you know, did he have some kind of ability or whatever.
And there's her take on this, and which seems believable to me, is that initially Joseph
Smith probably knew that he was a charlatan, and that there were some particular events
that made him begin to believe in him.
self and were so convincing that he even convinced his own immediate family that he was a
prophet. Like there was a he prayed over a woman who had a paralyzed arm and then suddenly
just walked out of the room and she lifted her arm. And a lot of people saw that and they
said, whoa, you know, now there's all kinds of explanations one could give that. And obviously
if somebody's a Mormon, they're going to say that was a miracle through the prayers of Joseph
Smith, but
Yeah, I mean, he's obviously drawing on some of these same kind of traditions, but there's
significant difference even in what he claims.
Of course, to me, the most significant difference is that I don't think it happened the way
he said, you know, but it's worth it.
Someone's driving through Pennsylvania of near Northeastern corner, Pennsylvania.
It's worth going.
It's worth taking the tour.
If you're interested in Mormon history, which I am.
So does that answer your question, Dan, from Ontario, California?
Yeah, that answers some of it.
Some of it.
You have a spicy take.
What's your spicy take?
We do have Mormon listeners, right?
So just although they seem to be pretty thick skinned,
our Mormon listeners are very thick skinned.
They're still with us.
So God bless you guys.
We do love you.
My spicy take is that actually Captain Janeway is the best captain in all of Star Trek.
Okay.
Now you've lost all of the critical.
Cut that guy off.
You've lost all credibility.
every episode she tries to blow up her own ship.
And another endless tedious argument with Ticote. Come on.
The clerk did blow up his ship, which makes him a much lesser cap.
So new.
He was in a dangerous spot, but you notice when Kirk blows up his ship,
there's this whole elaborate thing you have to go through to activate the self
to strike. Like J way was so ready to do it. It was just like coach.
the
chainway one blow up the ship.
Boom.
Like she had it like on a speed dial, right?
Just to hit the button, blow the ship up.
That's part of the season.
Will you please once tell us the story of why you got kicked out of the temple?
And I'm pretty sure it was the one in Redlands.
No, it was not.
It was the one in Salt Lake City.
Okay.
But there's not time to fill that story now.
I will at some point at some point.
Maybe if the Lord is coming.
And then you will know that the end is coming. Right.
Well, let me, let me add on the question. Let me add a piece on the question.
Okay. To me, the issue is central to our argument last time and this time is connection.
That there is a direct chain of direct connection going down through the centuries,
right? Right. Going back to the apostles, right? Yeah. And to me, the biggest thing that,
that rules what Joseph's.
Smith is saying they're out of court is the whole idea of the great apostasy.
Right. The idea that that chain was fundamentally broken for.
That's right. 1800 years restoring the church or close to 17 disappears all those years.
Right. And by the way, Mormonism is not alone in that.
Yeah, a lot of a lot of trick right.
There are a lot of restorationist groups.
Yeah, a lot of even like reform groups will talk about, you know, the Pauline gospel being lost
and being recovered by Martin Luther.
Right. And to me, any theological viewpoint that requires the gates of hell to have prevailed
against the church for some number of centuries, I rule it out of court. There you go. That's
just my perspective on it, right? Like, and that's that I think is the point of discontinuity
between what we're saying and what Joseph Smith said. Yep. All right. Well, thank you very much
That's what we're calling, Dan.
But IE.
All right, all right. We will take one more call. Oh, we have we have Yvonne calling from New York
So Yvonne welcome to Lord Spears podcast
Hi, father's welcome. I'm thank you
Captain Janeway is the best, but I'm not gonna argue that point. I'm just gonna say it
Curious wow
Also you you partly answered my question
I think when William called and he asked about was Moses a prophet.
or a priest and you had said that yes he was a prophet.
And my question is regarding that, that was part A of my question which you already answered.
And that part B regarding that had to do with like you know how in the Nicene Creed,
it's his the Holy Spirit, both by the prophets, right.
And also regarding like the authority given to like Peter in his epistle,
He talks about how he has.
authority. But then he goes on to say like he equates prophecy with teaching which I was
going to ask like is that the same thing, Prophecy and teaching which I think you had already
said yes to that in a previous episode about prophecy. But then also he says that prophecy
came not in all time by the will of man but holy men of God speak as they were moved by
the Holy Ghost. So my question is that the Holy
the third person of the Trinity being actually God, right?
If a prophet is being used as a vessel
by the Holy Spirit, then in the last episode,
when you were speaking about how Moses was given free will
to kind of decide in rule and this and that,
it almost sounded like he was speaking separately from God
from God.
whereas according to the Nicene Creed and then this letter from Peter, it made, you know,
I was under the impression that every word spoken by the prophet was spoken by the Holy Spirit.
And then also real quick, when Jesus is to the Pharisees, you nullify the word of God
for the sake of your tradition. That sounds like there is a separation, like the Pharisees
making a word that nullifies God's word, which would mean that the Holy Spirit would intend
one thing and they were not allowing themselves to be used as a vessel.
Does that question make sense?
Or should I rephrase it or was it rambly?
It was a little bit rambly, but I think not.
It was fine.
Yeah.
No, it was fine.
It was fine.
It's fighting it.
It's basically about the Holy Spirit.
like role when somebody who is in a position of a prophet is speak.
at what point do they say, oh this is me talking separate from the Holy Spirit?
Yeah, right. So I'm going to say those aren't separate. Yeah, right. Those aren't two different things.
things. So like the Scriptures, every word of the Scriptures,
And the quote you gave is on point from St. Peter, right?
The everywhere to the scriptures, right? God
Right ultimately comes from God comes from the Holy Spirit's guidance, right?
We would say the decisions of the church councils are guided by the Holy Spirit. All these things are guided by the Holy Spirit
Right, apart from God, we can do nothing, right?
But that doesn't mean that
all the humans involved are robots,
Right or just be
and this is part of this dilemma in sort of Western thinking. It's part of Plato-Brain
that like, it's what produces things like Calvinism, where a Calvinist will say, well, look,
unless God is in absolute control and He does everything and is just puffeting everything,
And how can he predict the future?
Right? Because someone could make a choice and ruin everything, right? And that's not
the understanding of Scripture, right? The understanding of Scripture is that there's
a human being and if you read, especially the New Testament in Greek and the original Greek,
You could very much tell it's different humans who wrote this.
Some of their Greek is really bad.
It's not good Greek. It's not all the same Greek
Right a human sat down and wrote this say Paul sat down and wrote a letter to the church in Rome
He didn't sit down and say well today. I'm going to write some scripture
Right or he didn't go into a trance and wake up and the Holy Spirit had written this right he wrote a letter
Helping them solve their problems making rulings say this is this is what you should do
by my authority as an apostle right and we believe that
that God was
guiding him in the decisions he made and the rulings he made and what he said. And then God guided
the church into including the epistles we have from St. Paul in Scripture, including those and not
other things St. Paul wrote. He wrote other letters to the Corinthians we know that aren't in the
Bible, but the Holy Spirit guided the church so that the ones that God wanted to be there in the
in the New Testament or there in the New Testament.
Right? But again...
Then God didn't have to take away anyone's free will all along the line in order to do that.
So both of those things are always true.
People are always acting freely and using the abilities and gifts and the authority and
all the things that God gave them freely and God judges them for how they use those things
and how they apply those things.
And at the same time, God the Holy Spirit.
is guiding all of human history toward an end.
It's a little through.
And in terms of the other piece with the Pharisees,
with the Kerban rule, again, it's important that we take it in context, right?
What is the tradition that Christ is talking about?
The tradition Christ is talking about is the Kerban rule.
What is the Kerban rule?
The Pharisees said, right, that you could
good.
dedicate all of your possessions to the temple essentially.
Okay? You could say, you know what, when I die instead of leaving
all of my property and all of my belongings to my heirs,
I'm going to leave it to God. I'm going to give it to the temple.
Okay?
Now, there's a thing wrong with that.
Right? That's, I mean, it's a tradition in that it's not in the
Tora, excellent.
explicitly, right, to do that or that you can do that. But they ruled that, you know,
hey, this is something that would be allowable, right, within the Torah for you to do this.
Christ isn't criticizing people for doing that, right? But here's the thing. Some of the
Pharisees were then using that and saying, for example, well, I've dedicated all my belongings
to the temple when I die.
That means I can...
can't go giving my, give money to the poor.
Yeah.
I can't spend this money to take care of my parents.
I can't spend this money to these things
because I've already promised it to God.
I'm doing legacy giving, right?
And so they were using that, they were exploiting that, right?
And in the way they exploited it,
they were not honoring their father and mother.
and you're neglecting mercy.
and compassion for the poor, right?
All of these things that the Torah commands,
they were using this tradition to try to get around.
And so Christ was criticizing them
for how they were abusing the tradition.
He wasn't saying there's anything wrong with the tradition.
I don't think any Christian today would say
it's wrong for someone in their will
to leave some portion or even all of their possessions
to the church if they want to, right?
I don't think it's a Christmas.
say, no, that's evil, right?
But if someone did that,
and then like their child was in trouble
and they refused to help their child,
then we'd have a problem, right?
Then they'd be like, whoa, right?
Like leaving money to the church is a good thing,
but you have other responsibilities
with the money that God gave you,
and you leaving the money to the church
doesn't let you off the hook for those other responsibilities.
So that's the discussion Christ is having.
And I know it gets...
take it out of context a lot. And I know a lot of our Protestant friends, we've used that
to say, therefore, all traditions are bad, right? Which is just sort of woefully out of
context. Like there's no way to get that, right? The, the, it's a distortion to even say
that Christ is saying that particular tradition is bad, let alone all traditions are bad,
Right. But, right, it's how they're abusing, right, that tradition, right?
And so he's saying, like, look, yeah, you're following your tradition, but you're violating the commandments, right?
That's not good. Right. Yeah. Yeah.
All right. Well, thank you very much for calling you, Vaughn. I hope that helps.
All right. Well, rolling on now to the here in the third half,
succeeding the apostles is a successor. The same thing as a, as an apostle. They just, you know,
Apostles better than part being a failure, I guess. Part duh.
Right. So the Apostles, of course, are directly commissioned by Jesus in person.
Right? That's and that's sort of one of the requirements. Right? And so that's why St. Paul is
always pressing that point. Right. Because there are people who don't want to acknowledge him as
having the same apostolic authority because he wasn't one of the
the 12 with Jesus, right, like during his earthly life. And that's why he's always stressing
the fact that no, he was directly commissioned by Jesus in person, right, after the resurrection.
And that Christ actually appears to have several more times after that in the book of
Acts. But, apostleship stops with the apostles, meaning they don't make the next generation
of people in apostles. They don't appoint apostles to replace them.
Yeah.
Right. We don't get in the pastoral epistles in first and second Timothy and Titus. Here are the requirements to be an apostle.
Yeah, there's going to be any more right.
Um,
in general, anybody who refers to themselves as an apostle in the contemporary world is someone to be marked and avoided the same Paul.
I mean, the new apostolic reformation is not actually apostolic.
No, not remotely.
Hot remote.
There's no sense of the word apostolic in which the NAR is apostolic.
They do not teach with the Apostles' teach.
There is no line of succession. There is no, I mean, there's like just zero.
Yeah.
Anyway, the Mormons have a better claim.
Do you have a stall for information?
So uh, what you have?
what we have discussed is a Piscopos, right?
Well, we'll become bishops, right?
And pressmenors, and of course, Deacons, but of course,
people don't argue that much about Deacons.
So, I said, well, well, that's a whole other set of issues.
Yes, yes, I'm just...
remain to yeah throwing that out there um
We come with your creeping liberalism again. I know where you're I know you crazed progressive on some days
I'm some kind of alt-right, you know, radical on other days. I'm some kind of
liberal progressive whatever and yeah
Today I'm feeling like a radical anti-centrist like me. That's right
Shire party. That's my party. Shire party.
Yeah, so and the word you will sometimes get, and this is mostly from our Protestant friends,
is they will say, well, in the New Testament, you know, this idea of Episcopalus or Bishop
and Presbyter, they're kind of, they're kind of used interchangeably.
Yeah.
There's not really Bishops.
There's just these two kind of things. There's like press-papers.
and then there's there's decons, right?
Presbyter's slash bishops and decons.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And they lean toward wanting to use press matter, right?
Yeah, of course.
The bishop thing, that's an outlier, okay?
And so they argue, see, you know, there's not sort of a clear
three tier structure necessarily, right?
Of bishop pre-steak.
Now there certainly isn't a history of the church,
but they'll argue the New Testament.
if you just go to
the New Testament that's that clear. There's a few problems with this idea that the titles
Episcopal Serbishop and Presbyter are interchangeable. First one is if you read the Apostolic Fathers
and New Testament scholars and and patricistic scholars never talk to each other so that's why
people don't know this. Right? You know that from papias and other apostolic
fathers.
They frequently refer to the apostles as prespitors.
Yep.
Okay, so Saint John, who wrote the gospel, right,
referred to by PBS as an elder.
There's a prespitor. Okay.
I don't think any of our prophets and friends would say that the title of
apostle or the title prespitor are interchangeable.
No. Okay.
So that
That tells us that the term presbyter or elder gets more broadly applied beyond just an
office of presbyter proper.
There are people who are apostles, there are other people who get referred to as elders
who aren't necessarily a presbyter in the sense that first or second to be he talks about
Presbyters, right?
The other problem with this interchangeable idea is that interchangeable works both ways.
Yeah, if something is equivalent one way, then it should be equivalent the other way too.
Right. So, while we have lots of examples of apostles and bishops, Episcopie, being called pressmeners,
We have no instances of run of the bill.
Presbyters be referred to as apostles or bishops.
Yeah. Yeah.
And so apostles and bishops frequently called
presbyters as well.
Right. It just means elder.
It's like just yeah, respect for leader, you know, religious
leaders. But people with the actual office of
presbyter don't get called those other two things ever.
Yeah, it's not interchangeable.
Yeah. I mean, and the other thing is is that no matter where you
New Testament or the Apostolic Fathers. I get super duper clear in the epistles of St.
Ignatius of Antioch, who is writing at the very latest, like maybe 107, maybe earlier.
I mean, this guy is a disciple of the Apostle John. It's very clear that there's always three levels.
So no matter what word you use as a title, there's always one man who's at the center of the community.
And then there's...
another group that's around him, and then there's another group that are the ones assisting.
Right.
And traditionally, these are called bishops, presbyters, and deacons.
But you might also call them the apostle and the presbyters slash bishops and deacons.
But there's always one and then a group and then it would be apostles, presbyters and deacons.
Right.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Because if, and this is where this is going, we'll just spoilers telegraph it.
Right.
Bishop is essentially six-
to an apostle, then when there are apostles around, there aren't going to be bishops around.
Yeah, because you don't need a successor when you've got the original.
Right.
You're going to have apostles, prespitors, and decons.
But then when you start losing apostles, the apostles start appointing successors that
is going to shift over time as your apostles go away, right?
To being bishop, prespitor, decon.
And while there are still some apostles around, you're going to have a mix.
It's up, please.
You're going to have an apostle and presbyters and Deacon.
Other places you're going to have bishop presbyters and Deacon.
Right?
But part of the solution to this with the way the term presbyter is used in these sources
is that you have to understand that this is the Greek word that translates the Hebrew
Zaken, which means elder, right?
And the term Zachan, all the members of the Sanhedrin had that title.
senior scribes had that title.
Other rabbis and teachers who were prominent
in various places, in the Jewish diaspora, had that title.
So they're using that same honorary title
for all kinds of people who hold authority in the church,
not just for the people who have that particular office
of breastbutter, right?
But using it for them also.
And so in terms of isolating, you know, this sort of nascent office of bishop, which is nascent in the New Testament,
because the New Testament is being written by the apostles. So de facto the apostles are there
while they're writing, right? And active in the churches while they're writing,
we get it that by asking, what is Timothy? Yeah, what office does Timothy have?
or Titus.
These people who Christ, St. Paul appoints, St. Paul is appointed by Christ. St. Paul appoints Timothy and Titus to be overseers of Iskopee, which is comes from a Hebrew term for a herdsman.
That's really where that comes from.
And that's why that gets translated as pastor in Latin, which pastor in Latin by the way is the word for shepherd.
So...
Going back to the first half, if you think it's wrong to call someone doctor so and so or father so and so, but it's cool to call them shepherd so and so.
I, hey, we have one shepherd and that's Christ, right?
Wait, are you saying so book was some kind of bishop?
Yes, that's what I'm saying.
No, matter shepherd and mass effect also.
I'll let you play in femme-shap then no.
No women's ordination.
in bio-aware games. So Timothy and Titus get sent, right, and get put in charge of these
areas, in charge of these regions. By St. Paul, he's doing it self-consciously when you
read first and second Timothy and Titus, knowing that his life in this world is coming to
an end. And he is appointing them to continue his ministry in these different areas to be
a successor.
And one of the things he tells them to do, for example, he tells Titus,
Titus 1 verse 5, to appoint prespitors in every city.
Did St. Paul think any given prespitor could just go around making more prespitors
as many as he wanted in every city he went to?
To say no.
And part of the reason I would say no is if you look at Acts 14 verse 23,
it talks about St. Paul, it is journeys appointing prespitors in every city.
It's a
same language. So he's telling Titus to continue his ministry. And part of his
ministry was appointing presbyters in each city. But then what is Titus? He is a
successor to Saint Paul who stands over the presbyters and has the authority to
ordain them to lay hands on them and ordain them and make them presbyters. And that
And it is how that laying out of hands.
That exact same ritual that was done starting with Moses and Joshua to pass on and convey
that authority is exactly what the apostles were doing.
We read about that in the New Testament.
So in Acts 6, verse 6, they bring the first seven deacons in front of the apostles.
They pray they lay their hands on them.
Let's give them authority's decons.
Second Timothy 1 verse 6.
He says to St. Paul says to St. Timothy,
for this reason I remind you and in deflame the gift of God,
which is in you through the laying on of my hands.
St. Paul laid his hands on St. Timothy to make him his successor.
In doing that, this was not just a designation,
this was not just a right or a prayer,
through him laying on hands.
Sorry, Protestants who don't believe
more nation as a sacrament.
Timothy received within himself the flame of the gift of God. Yeah. First Timothy 5 verse 22,
he says to him, do not be hasty in the laying on of hands. Do not take part in the sins of others,
keep yourself pure. So bishops are ants. Yes, that's exactly what it is. Right, you don't just
or day and everybody, and anybody.
Right why why why is that dangerous?
Because you're giving them authority with that authority they can do a lot of damage
Yeah, if it and you work giving them any authority then who cares it wouldn't matter. Yeah, right?
It's an online ordination certificate, right?
Universal Life Church. Yes, like doesn't mean anything
And then in Hebrews 6 1 and 2
Right? And this is we're all good in the argument now, homily from St. Paul, right?
But it says, therefore, let us leave the elementary doctrine of Christ and go on to maturity,
not laying again a foundation of repentance from dead works of faithfulness toward God,
of instruction about baptisms, the laying on of hands, the resurrection of the dead and
eternal judgment. So this is a list of things that the Jewish Christians, to whom St. Paul
speaking already know all about
and he doesn't need to say.
anything about. Yeah, this is the elementary stuff that you repent from dead
works. You become faithful to God, right? Your baptized the laying out of
hands, ordination, resurrection of the dead, and eternal judgment. You guys know
all about that as Jewish Christians. Now let's talk about some deeper stuff.
Right? Meaning that these Jewish Christians who he's talking to in the first
century already had this understanding of what laying on of hands,
or nation in the
church meant, meaning it was a carryover of the Jewish practice.
So this is a continuation of that original Jewish practice.
And so we see here, as St. Paul is appointing his successors,
part of the balance of what we're talking about in the last half
between individual authority or personal authority.
and primacy, and then the multiplicity, right, the conciliarity, right?
And part of that takes the form of regional sovereignty. St. Paul sends people to places.
Yeah, he appoints presbyters in cities. Yes, and he sends Timothy and St. Titus to particular places
to be bishops, to be his successor over this region, over this place.
Yeah, right?
Does it give them all the same place?
Does it?
send them roaming the earth like pain and kung fu to go from place to place
at just right gunslingers and you know wandering bishops exercise your
authority as you see fit wherever you see fit right and so by assigning
these particular regions then you have a group of people with authority over
particular churches, particular right communities, who can now gather in Council.
to solve larger issues.
And we see so these successors like St. Clement in Rome, writing epistles.
First Clement, he writes to the Church of Corinth, because apparently even after all of St. Paul's
letters, they still needed some more, right?
To make rulings and to exercise this authority.
And so just like we saw with Moses.
Apostolic succession has these two elements corresponding to the body of the soul, the body
being the physical, the laying on of hands, this chain reaching back to the apostles that
can be documented, right?
This material connection, and then there is a soul to it, right?
Which is a sharing of the Apostolic faith, right?
gives life right to the ministry of that person.
But the person who's had the laying on of hands if they don't have the sole part
Still has the authority
Hmm right no donatists here, right?
An atheist who has been properly ordained the things he does
Right? This baptism he does or baptisms, right?
he does is the Eucharist.
Really, he makes other rulings he makes until and unless he's deposed.
Right?
But even when he's deposed, that's not retroactive.
Like, oh, we gotta go back and re-baptize all those people he baptized because he was a
bum, right?
He was faithless, right?
Because he was like one of the Pharisees.
Because again, remember what Christ said to the Pharisees.
Said a lot of bad things about them personally, right?
about their life for the way they could do-
themselves. It's that there are other way to hell, right? But didn't say, therefore, don't listen
to anything they tell you, right? They still, they still have that authority. Okay, so there's this
primacy within regions, right? When they're gathering, as we talked about, and then there's also a
a primacy that develops from manifest holiness.
Yeah, the sense that some of them...
It's clear that they are set apart in a particular way by God.
They're particular gifts. They're wise. They're particularly holy.
And it's not an institutional right primacy.
It's that everyone just kind of deferstered that one because they can all see that they're holy.
Right.
So there are these kinds of primacies.
We're gonna narrow it on some things here because there were a lot of Pope questions
about our last episode, right?
So that's what we're going here at the end of our third half.
So yes, the Orthodox Church believes there's primacy.
Right?
We have Metropolitan's patriarchs.
Those are all bishops, those aren't separate offices.
Right?
And each of them is sovereign in their own city.
Yep.
And the Bishop of Homs,
Right is justice sovereign in Homs as the patriarch of anyok is in Damascus
Right
But the patriarch of anyok has primacy right in terms of the way in which things work
conciliatorally the way things work in
gatherings and when when the bishops come together
We absolutely believe in that we don't believe that like
like.
There is no privacy at all bishops are just identical, right?
Yeah, yeah
Also believe it or not this may shock some people orthodox and not orthodox alike
The other church has always taught petrion privacy
true
You don't have to look very far. Why we just had the feast of St. Peter and Paul or we're just about to I guess if you're on the old calendar
Read the liturgex, right?
Right? St. Peter's the Prince of the Apostles.
right all that stuff all that good stuff about St. Peter is there. Um, so
about Roman Catholic friends anytime a church father says anything positive
about St. Peter is, uh, Pope, right? Uh, no, that we don't deny that St. Peter had
probably talked about it. Last time St. Peter James John had this primacy. St. Peter
certainly one of them, right? And that primacy.
The Orthodox Church is also always taught get ready for this.
Didn't stop when St. Peter died. His successors have a kind of privacy too.
Right. In fact, you look no further than one of the former bishops of Rome.
St. Gregory the Deologist, also known as Pope St. Gregory the Great in the West.
Right. Who in his letters to the patriarch of Cotsett, Opal talks about the three petrineses.
Yeah, not just Rome.
but also Alexandria and Antioch.
Yes, and say those three, the reason those three churches
have a kind of primacy is because
Antioch and Rome are successors of St. Peter
and St. Mark, who was a successor of St. Peter,
went to Alexandria and became the Bishop there.
Right?
So you have three petriots, right?
And that was acknowledged.
by the way by Constantinople, which is why you see
and this way really break the hearts
of some of our Greek listeners.
And so I apologize in advance, but this is the truth.
You could look this up.
Historically true.
When Constantinople was founded,
it was not in any way connected with St. Andrew.
It's true.
I mean, that is a tradition that develops over time.
Yep.
St. Andrew did evangelize that area.
Okay, so it's not made up.
Right, but the connection to Saint Andrew becomes much more prominent a few centuries later, and that is not unrelated to the fact that Saint Andrew was Saint Peter's older brother.
The better brother, really.
And that Saint Andrew is a way of connecting Constantinople to Saint Peter and his primacy.
So we acknowledge Petroine primacy.
Right, that is not a thing that we deny.
So these folks who are like
Oh, it does seem like St. Peter was a leader of the early church.
I guess I got to become Roman Catholic.
No, you missed, you missed the plot, man.
Yeah.
I will.
And the dots like to make that work, you have to assume.
And there's no basis for this actually.
But that's why you have to assume it that the Bishop of Rome is Peter's soul
and exclusive successor.
Right.
but that is and
extension that Saint Peter was Christ only. Right. Right. Exactly. And neither one of those things
is present in the scriptures or present in the early church. And this is what gets to the issue.
This is what gets to the issue. From an orthodox perspective, the problem
with the way the Roman church has structured itself,
Since the couple is a century or two before the schism, is the
that the Bishop of Rome is the only Bishop in the Roman Church,
from our perspective,
meaning the authority given to bishops
as successors of the Apostles,
the Orthodox tradition,
the only Bishop who can really exercise that full authority
in the Roman Church is the Bishop of Rome himself.
all of the other bishops in the Roman
church are effectively press-fitters.
Yeah, and I mean this is they cannot rule authoritatively.
Right. And individually. Even as a council.
Obviously our Roman Catholic friends would disagree with that idea that there's no other
bishops in the church. But but like let's be clear about this.
If a council of the Roman Catholic church gathers,
the Pope does not have to obey them. He can call them. He can dismiss them. He can
and overrule them.
He has authority over them. He can hire and fire any bishop of the Catholic Church anywhere on earth.
He's the only one who can make bishops.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, others do the consecrating, whatever, but he's the one that has to approve every single,
episcopal consecration, which to us demotes them to presbyter. Yeah. Right.
So for us, a pressmanor, I'm a pressmanor, you're a pressmanor.
I'm a pepper, you're a pepper, he's a pepper.
pepper two. That's an old old that's why right. Okay. So I do not have a
Piscopal authority. I can't rule on things authoritatively. Thank God. Oh, you
know why? That's right. You know why? I can be asked by opinion. But I have a
bishop. And if my bishop comes in and says, well, let's even you're out to lunch.
And rules that I'm wrong, right? His ruling is what everyone has to follow, including me, not mine.
I have to be obedient to him. He can suspend me. He can defrock me. He can write.
He isn't authority over me.
The Bishop of Rome has that authority over every other bishop in the Roman Church.
Every other person who's called a bishop. That's what I mean when I say they're effectively devoted to presbyters.
The bishops in the
Roman Catholic Church have the kind of authority.
It's not that they have no authority,
but they have the kind of authority
that I have as a presbyter in the Orthodox Church.
Yeah, you're not the final rule.
I'm not the final rule.
I'm ASEA, right?
I am trusted by my bishop to handle most day-to-day small matters,
right?
Remember Moses?
Moses had appointed the presbyters, the elders,
to deal with the day-to-day stuff
They brought all the big stuff to him.
Yep, yep. Right. Moses is the bishop in this situation. Right. So that's what I mean. The bishop of
Rome is like Moses. He's a bishop. He has that authority and the people called bishops and archbishop
and cardinals and whatever else under him have the authority of prespitors under him.
And so this is the fundamental ecclesiastical divide.
Yeah. Right. The issue is not just like, oh, you orthodox just need to acknowledge that he has a
primacy. Well, the knowledge he has a primacy, a primate, different kinds of primacy. And then
it's based on St. Peter and all that stuff. Right. But that has to be coupled with him acknowledging
other bishops, not just the other patriarchs, every other bishops
in the Orthodox Church and every other bishop in the Roman Church as his equals.
Yeah, I mean, an authority and he fundamentally cannot do that and still be the Pope.
That's right. That you don't have a papacy. Does not work in the Roman Catholic system.
Then you don't have a papacy. I think it was, if I remember correctly, I mean correct me if I'm
wrong here, in the Council of Nicea, the canons with regards to primacy say that
You know, let all the bishops of a province or whatever do nothing without him who is first, in other words, the primate, but let him who is first do nothing without all the other bishops.
Right. Meaning that they're all dependent on each other. Right. Right. And from the perspective of Rome, right, they're cool with the first part of that. Right. Yes. None of you other bishops could do anything without the Pope.
right but they're not cool with the second half of that.
that the Pope can't do anything without all the other visions.
Yeah.
Because again, if you say that the other way, now you don't have a papacy.
And now you've got the Orthodox Church.
And would it be beautiful if we just had the Orthodox Church?
I think so.
So what this also means now that we've, you know, we've been all around tonight.
We hit the Mormons a little bit and we hit the
the proudest.
and we've hit the Roman Catholics now.
Now it's time to get some Orthodox people mad at us,
particularly in the United States.
That's right.
Uh, remember how we ended the last episode
talking about how Moses couldn't be wrong?
Yep, bishops can't be wrong.
In the Orthodox Church.
It's logically impossible for a bishop to be wrong.
Yeah.
Here's what we've been by that.
Is there ever how we
qualified this with Moses, right? We're not saying that bishops are always right about
their politics. I'm not saying they're always right about math and science. We're not
saying they're always right about predicting tomorrow's weather. That's not what we're
talking about. No. We're not even talking about a bishop can't be a heretic.
There's better parts of those.
This is him making the rulings of within his dies.
It'd be like, for instance,
when my wife says this is what we're having for dinner,
that is the decision that has been made
and that is what is being cooked
and that's what's gonna be on the table.
You can't be wrong about that
because she's the one cooking it.
That's right, exactly.
She can't be wrong about that
because she's the one who has that authority to do that.
So when the bishop says, this is the rule in my diocese,
he can't be wrong.
We're going to do this.
The thing is, within his authority,
he makes the rule,
make rulings to apply the canons and descriptors of the,
right?
Yeah.
And just like Jesus, when he's talking about the Pharisees,
he has all kinds of criticisms for them,
but he never tells people to disobey them or ignore them.
Yes.
He might even criticize the rulings they're making,
But he still doesn't pee
tell people to disobey them. Right. You know, it's like it's like it's like when my, you know,
when my wife and I are dealing with my children, she doesn't agree with every single ruling that I make.
She doesn't. But she will say things sometimes like, well, that is what your father said. So that is
the rule. Yeah. You know. So I'm just going to go ahead court controversy and you're taking
that bunch of people, right?
If an orthodox bishop says,
I don't want you to crucivate people anymore.
We're going to receive everyone by confession.
No baptisms, no christmations.
Right?
Anybody who's baptized in any vaguely Christian church received them by confession.
He's not wrong.
Yeah.
And if everyone who was received that way is just as legitimately an orthodox Christian.
That's right.
As the people received in another diocese by another bishop where that bishop says we're going to baptize everyone
Regardless of their background. Yeah. Yeah, all those people who he baptizes are just as legitimately orthodox Christians as all of these people received by confession
Yeah, and what and what people who you know, and they're both right both bishops are correct exactly and what people who would flip their lids about that may not know is that
both of those methods are
are sanctioned by the Ecumenical Councils.
So even a bishop who makes that decision,
it's not like he's making something up.
He's not.
Right.
Those are actually in the Ecumenical Councils.
Which again, are decided by-
I did the two misgrooms.
And then applied by bishops.
Right, that's their job.
That's their authority.
They have the authority to do that.
They're the ones making-
What's they do when it's done?
The people are received.
That's right.
There's, there's a-
I think it's from St. Theaticals of Fodtiki, maybe, where he was preaching some sermon about baptism
and someone who had been received into the church who had been part of a heretical group,
who had been received through some other method, I think, Christmas or whatever.
Heard this sermon and was so moved by it that he freaked out and like, you know,
I didn't really receive an Orthodox baptism and please, you know, do it.
And this guy had been in the church for years.
and the saint said to him, I would not
dare to baptize you, you were received already,
you are part of the church period.
Right.
Because the bishop has the authority to do that.
Yeah, because whoever the bishop was
that had received this other guy, he was authoritative.
He had, you know, and the saint recognized that
and simply, you know, he didn't say,
well, I have another opinion.
Yeah.
Well, what about this canon?
Right.
If a bishop ordained someone divorced,
I'm a bitch.
Uh, allows someone to continue to serve as a priest after being divorced. If a Bishop
allows a priest to remarry after being widowed and remain a priest, if a, uh, Bishop
decide, and these are all things that have happened at various times in various places.
Yeah. Not just all contemporary times either. If you're thinking like, oh, well, there's
all this Lucy Goosey stuff down. No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, 15th, 13th, 12th
I mean read the canons.
Read the cannon.
all of those cannons, which have a lot of weird scenarios in them come up because that thing happened.
Right. So at every bishop who made every one of those rulings was right when they made those
rulings. And the bishops, sometimes the same bishop when he made the opposite ruling in a different
case was right when he made the opposite ruling. Yeah. Now related to all of that because
I'm sure some people like, well, wait a minute. What about if a bishop really is off off the
the reservation.
Right.
Well, that's the question.
It's accountability.
We're all big accountability.
Because especially about other people,
not ourselves, but other people.
That's right.
The truth is that sometimes bishops do get overruled,
but the really important thing to notice is by whom.
Right.
By whom.
So the fact that this is not, the church is not a democracy.
The fact that your bishop is not accountable to you,
You
I mean, he's not accountable.
That's right.
Right?
Because first of all, there's that
consult conciliarity thing we were talking about.
It takes two or three bishops to make a bishop,
but the bishops of the Senate can get together
and depose a bishop.
Yep.
They make him not a bishop anymore.
Take that authority away from him.
Right?
Now if that authority's taken away from him,
as we said before, that doesn't invalidate
all the stuff he did while he was a bishop
while he had that a th-
That's all done.
I mean, they could overrule it because they have that authority to do that.
Right.
Well, they could go forward.
There are things you can't undo.
Right.
But there are some things you can, like, for instance, the supposed priest, your name, but
that's still not undoing it because that person was still a priest or the priest.
Yeah.
Or like if a bishop, an airing bishop, deposes someone, the synod could say that was unjust
where restoring you.
But he still wasn't a priest during the period in which he was
opposed. Right. That's right. So you're not undoing it is what I mean. Yeah. Yeah. Right. You could moving forward. You could go in a different direction, but you can't undo what he did. Right. Um,
So they're accountable to the other bishops. Right. If the other bishops break communion, he's not an orthodox bishop anymore. If they depose him, he's not a bishop anymore. If they write there, all these things that they can do. So there is that direct accountability there. Right.
But more importantly,
And yes, this is more important.
And part of our problem as modern people is we don't really think this is more important.
I don't know if it's because we don't really believe in God or if it's because we don't
really believe in the resurrection of the dead.
But it's got to be one of the two.
Right.
Is that for some reason we think accountability to God doesn't count.
Yeah, like God's not going to do anything you guys.
Right?
This is this is what the Old Testament was talking about was is the fool says that their heart there is no God so a lot of us are a little foolish, right?
We somehow think that if someone escapes this life without being held accountable.
Oh, they have to be accountable to me, right?
That somehow they've gotten away with it and there was no accountability. I
Would much rather be judged by my fellow humans than by God.
right
which is more important that we expose the bad financial dealings of some bishop or other church authority figure now,
so that I can hold them accountable, right?
Or they die in their sins and God holds them accountable.
Now, if our desire to hold them accountable came from a desire to see them repent, right?
So they wouldn't face the judgment of God, that would be different.
But I don't see a lot of that.
No, I think it's mostly about making people feel better or feel like they're right or
that they're winning.
Yes, I think it's anger, personal anger, and pride, and you have to be accountable to me.
Right?
You have to be accountable to me.
You have to answer to me, person who's already over.
Which?
I mean, the example we see in the scriptures.
Some people who are being trottened down by those in authority is that they cry out to
God for vindication, and that He will vindicate them.
That's what we see from the righteous is that they cry out to God for vindication.
Right.
This is why St. James, one of those bishops with great primacy, in his epistle said, not
Many of you should become teeth.
my brothers, for you know that we, you teach, will be judged with greater
strictness. There's a greater judgment. And I've said this a bunch in my Bible
studying and stuff, right? But this is real, okay? When you stand in front of
Christ's judgment seat on the last day, you are going to have to give an account
for yourself. If you are married, you're going to have to give an account to
Christ for yourself and your spouse.
If you have married and have children, you will have to give an account to Christ for you,
for your spouse, for each of your children.
Because you have authority over them, as their parent.
I is a priest, I'm going to have to give an account for myself, for my wife, for every
one of my parishioners who I've ever had at any church I've served at.
My bishop is going to have to give an account for every
a single clergy person and every single human
and every one of his churches.
People don't want that when they want to get ordained.
There's a lot of things they want.
They don't want that awesome responsibility.
They don't want that weight on their shoulders.
They don't want a shoulder,
the sins of the people who there is.
authority over. But that's the reality of what it means. That's the accountability
that our bishops have that goes with that authority. Okay? The bishop who decides to
let somebody get remarried, it's good to have to explain that to Christ. Why that was the
right thing to do. Why that was the best thing to do for that person's salvation.
These are decisions that
that bishops make likely.
And having the authority and responsibility to make them
is not a light thing, right?
And this isn't just theoretical or imaginary or a parable.
This is real, right?
This is real.
I'm going to have to explain to Christ why I told the people
what I tell them in confession.
Why advise them to do certain things or not do certain?
things. All of that, every word I can't about, I'm gonna have to give an account for it.
Right? So, nobody's getting away with anything. Nobody's unaccountable. Okay? And the kind of
accountability that people with authority in the church have to Christ, being accountable
to some people or group of people who are a parish councilor or something, like that's
nothing. That's
get out of here with that, right?
That, you know, that's all ego, if you think that's real.
So yeah, this is gonna end up being my closing comments, I think.
Because, oh, yeah.
All right.
Because I'm gonna be done after this, I think.
But, yeah, this is, this is, this is the real deal.
This is where the rubber meets the road.
This is what actually
being an Orthodox Christian. Not a not a Protestant who's read a lot of church
fathers and owns a copy of the rudder, but being an actual Orthodox Christian,
this is part of what it means is realizing what authority means,
realizing what real accountability before God is. And therefore submitting and
being obedient to the authorities that God has put over you.
So you can go ahead and finish up. All right, I get the last word.
Yeah. One of the things you'll hear people cynically
say sometimes when talking about church authority is, they just expect us to pray, pay, and obey.
You know, be good little churchgoers, give your money, be obedient. And
you know, as Americans, right? That sounds horrifying. That's a recipe for oppression.
This country wasn't founded on that.
And it's true, it wasn't.
But that is what Christianity is, actually, to pray, to worship God, to request all the
good things for our salvation from Him, to pay, to give, to give to Christ.
our time or money or our talents.
And to be obedient.
And I know that a lot of people when they encounter the Orthodox Church for the first time, and I see that we have this tradition of obedience.
I think because the United States of America does not have a tradition of obedience, really has a tradition of disobedience and really lords that.
You know, examine everything for yourself.
for yourself, right? That then seeing that obedience is part of the Orthodox tradition,
it can and interpreting that, understanding that, and practicing seeing that can be
very skewed, right? So on the one hand, you have people who they'll go to their priest, their
their confessor, their spiritual father.
a blessing to do a lot of different things that they could just decide for themselves,
you know, really. And so it's extreme, you know, and I think that some of that probably
comes from reading monastic related literature where that kind of obedience is the norm in
a monastery, although maybe not as extreme as some people might think. And then on the other
hand it's really the sense of
Well, I'm going to decide whether what my priest or my bishop or my patriarch or my
Holy Sinad are doing is right or wrong.
And if they're right, then I'll go along with it.
But if they're not, then I'll not go along with it.
I'm going to resist.
Right?
I'm going to call them to account.
I'm going to expose them.
And emotionally, that feels great to do that.
You feel righteous.
feel you're the underdog, stick it to the man, speak truth to power, all that kind of stuff.
But as we have seen, very, very clearly throughout the scriptures and throughout the whole history of
the church, that is not the way that airing church leaders are held accountable. As we just said,
Does it mean that they're never held accountable?
But that's not the way they're held accountable. I do not hold my bishop accountable. I do not.
Speaking as a presbyter, as a priest, my job in particular, I've had actually people tell me,
like, well, if your bishop said or did this, then you shouldn't go along with that. You know, you
should resist. I'm sorry, but that is a complete misunderstanding of particularly what the role of
the President is.
President's job is to execute the
the policies of his bishop because the bishop is the pastor of the diocese of every parish.
He is the pastor, and if a president cannot obey his bishop and execute his will,
then it cannot be his president, either he needs to be deposed from the priesthood,
or he needs to request a release to be with a different bishop.
You know, so this idea of priests in resistance that is not a thing that is not
how this works. It's not how it works. It's very, very clear with regards to the Office of the
priesthood. But the truth also is that we all, we all are supposed to be practices obedience.
And yes, it is a freely chosen obedience, but that doesn't mean that you listen to every word
and every command and decide for yourself, okay, I'm going to choose this one. I'm going to choose
this one I'm going to choose this one. No, no, no, no, no, no, no, that'll be like,
deciding for myself, you know, I'm going to be faithful to my wife in this way, but not this way,
this way, but not this way, right? Either I'm faithful to my wife or not, either I'm obedient to
my bishop or not. Obedience means that sometimes my will is not going to be an alignment with the will
of the one to whom I owe that obedience. And if I always, if I only obey when my will aligns with
his will, then that's not obedience.
Not to him anyway, that's obedience to me.
Against...
that's as we said earlier, that's that's doing what's right in my own eyes.
I mean, scripture is very, very clear about that. That that, yes, you can have your conscience
bound by the spiritual authority over you. That is the way that it works. You cannot get around
that you can't. There is no Orthodox tradition of rising up.
against your spiritual leadership and throwing them down. That is not a thing.
That doesn't mean that spiritual leadership in the Orthodox Church is absolute. It's not.
It is under God. It is under a bishop. It is under a synod of bishops.
Ultimately, it's under God. And that actually makes a difference. I mean, Father, you said
that earlier, I'm not sure people believe in God or not
when they act this way.
I think it's
It's a functional atheism. Like God's not going to do anything. And so we we have to you know brothers and sisters
We have to or or maybe worse
You know our righteous anger is is the Holy Spirit moving us
No, it's not Holy Spirit doesn't move you to do things that are against the Holy Scriptures
That's not true. That doesn't happen. It's not a thing. I
Know that's probably hard here for a lot of people, but I can tell you that
maturity in Christ is learning to let go of the need to be in charge. That is part
of what it means to be mature. And even church leaders who have a lot of authority,
The really mature ones are the ones who have set aside the need to be in charge.
And so since they've set aside that need, that desire for that, then they're actually able
to exercise that authority as servants, as those who are leading in love.
And I've met a few holy people in my life, including some who are bishops.
And when someone has that holiness.
It's certainly a lot easier to obey them.
A lot easier. You do it out of love and joy. It's just, wow, you know, I want to.
But there are also times when their holiness is not apparent to us.
I just put it that way. It doesn't mean they're not holy.
They might be and I just can't see it.
And we know from the scriptures that those who live under an oppressive and wrong
and messed up leadership.
that the righteous received that as from the Lord
as being a call to repentance,
that we're being afflicted so that we may repent.
That doesn't mean that that wicked ruler isn't wicked.
God uses wicked rulers,
over and over again in the scriptures, over and over again.
But it does mean that receiving that wicked rule
is for our repentance.
So for suffering, the response is repent.
God will hold the oppressors accountable.
Our task is to be faithful.
And yes, pray.
Hey, obey.
Because it turns out that that's actually the path
to the kingdom of heaven.
It really is.
So that is our show for tonight.
Thank you, everyone, for listening.
if you didn't happen to get through to a sl-
this time around. We'd just like to hear from you. You can email us at Lordofspirit.nationfaith.com.
You can message us through our Facebook page. You can also leave us a voice mail at SpeakBiped.com.
Slash Lord of Spirits. And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need
help to find a parish, then go to Orthodoxintro.org.
that's hidden a brand new life around the bend.
And if you're on Facebook, you can follow our page,
you can join our big discussion group,
you can leave reviews, ratings on your podcast apps,
but most importantly, please share this show
because word of mouth is how this thing works.
And finally, be sure to go to www.ActionFate.com
Stroke Support and help make sure we and lots of others
are able to podcast or stay on the air.
There were times when I lost a dreamer to found the trail
and at the end was you,
so path you've taken, a path I've taken,
the choices up to you, my friend.
Thank you, goodnight, God bless you.
This lane to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verse 6